<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ian's Blog.</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/</link><description>Ian's Blog.</description><atom:link href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:ian@ianbarton.co.uk"&gt;Ian Barton.&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2019 14:12:19 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>README and List of Pages to Update.</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2019-09-26-readme-fixes/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description></description><category>mountaineering</category><category>tripreport</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2019-09-26-readme-fixes/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 17:58:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Blog Makeover.</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2019-08-26-blogmakeover/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
My blog has languished for a few years. There are a number of reasons: time
pressure, laziness and a few problems with Pelican. I have decided to use
Nikola and my static site generator. I have converted the text in all the old
posts to work with &lt;a href="http://getnikola.com"&gt;Nikola&lt;/a&gt;. However, there is a lot of work to update all the
embedded photos. At the moment a lot of posts have embedded html which is
incompatible with Nikola, so raw html and not photos are displayed! I am
steadily working my through old posts fixing this.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2019-08-26-blogmakeover/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2019 15:46:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Change of Blog url.</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2019-09-23-changed-url/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I have decided to move my blog from the original &lt;a href="http://ian-barton.com"&gt;http://ian-barton.com&lt;/a&gt; to
&lt;a href="http://ianbarton.co.uk"&gt;http://ianbarton.co.uk&lt;/a&gt; . All the pages from the original site are here. If you
go to the old url, you should be automatically be redirected here.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2019-09-23-changed-url/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2019 15:46:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Backpacking Kit List</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2015-09-24-backpacking-kit-list/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I haven't included what I would be wearing, which would usually
include a Rab Vapour Ride Lite jacket. In hot weather this would go
inside the rucksack. In warm weather I wear Rab Treklite trousers. In
cooler weather I wear my Mammut Base Jumps.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is what I would typically take on a Spring/Autumn trip. In
summer, if the forecast was good, I wouldn't take either the cagoule,
or the waterproof over trousers, but would substitute either a Montane
???? or Marmot Dr-Clime windshirt.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I prefer to camp high up, so it's usually chilly in the evening and
early mornings. The Montane prism jacket, worn over my base layer
keeps me nice and warm. The Montane prism trousers
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="hsides"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Item&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Weight (g)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Rucksack POD Black Ice&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;1780&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Green silnylon stuff sack&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Orange silnylon stuff sack&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Yellow Exped stuff sack&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;37&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Compass&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;2 x AA cells&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;48&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;TekNet rechargeable battery&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;176&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Micro usb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Phone&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;224&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Panasonic camera&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;435&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;2 x GoPro batteries&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Pot cosy&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;34&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;GoPro&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;135&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Sun glasses and case&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;72&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Kindle&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;299&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Prism jacket&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;446&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Prism trousers&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;323&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Montane Cag&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;293&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Headtorch&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;176&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Merino leggings&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;159&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Merino top&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;183&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Socks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;79&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Map&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;84&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Ortlieb map case&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;70&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Garmin eTrex&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;186&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Tyvek footprint&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Trowel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Fire steel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;49&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Berghaus paclite waterproof trousers&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;217&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Alpkit BruPot&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;266&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;X-Mug&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;32&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Titanium long handled spoon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Spork&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Primus Gravity&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;300&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Gas canister (250g)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;300&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;3 x Freeze dried meal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;360&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;5 x Hot chocolate sachets&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;63&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Platypus x 2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;78&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Travel Tap&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;297&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Rab Alpine 400 sleeping bag (inc. stuff sac)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;938&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Exped Synmat UL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;396&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Exped pillow&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;56&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Tent (TN Superlite Voyager)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;926&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Poles&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;424&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Pegs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;210&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Supermarket carrier bags X 2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;10579&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>review</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2015-09-24-backpacking-kit-list/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2015 17:59:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Decathlon Triban 500se</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2015-03-02-decathlon-triban-500SE/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Last year I bought a Giant Defy 2. However, I didn't want to ride it
through all the mud and salt in the winter months, so decided to buy a
cheap bike to use in winter. I did quite a bit of research and decided
to get a Decathlon Triban 500 SE. There is a more detailed review of the Triban 500SE
&lt;a href="http://road.cc/content/review/116333-btwin-triban-500-se-road-bike"&gt;road.cc&lt;/a&gt; .
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had to go into Decathlon with my daughter to buy some skiing
equipment and had  chance to look at the 500SE. It seemed to be a
decent bike for the price and I had read several positive reviews. I
ended up coming out of the store with one.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Decathlon Triban 500SE&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2015-03_triban/IMG_20150203_132015.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Decathlon Triban 500SE"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2015-03_triban/IMG_20150203_132015.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
After a few local rides of between 20 and 40 miles I was quite
impressed. The microshift gears (3x8) weren't as smooth a the Tiagra
on the Giant, but changes were positive with no missed gears. I have
got used to a compact gear set on the Giant, which I prefer to the
more traditional three front rings. However, there isn't anything
around here that's steep enough for me to need the small front ring,
so it wasn't really a problem. The saddle was a bit uncomfortable
after a couple of hours riding. However, it can't be that bad as I have a
better spare saddle at home and I haven't bothered changing it yet! The carbon
fork absorbs road vibrations nicely. The brakes do their job of
stopping you with minimum fuss, but I needed to pull a bit harder than
on the Giant.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I did change the tyres for Schwalbe Durano Plus folding tyres, as most
of my riding is along country lanes, where punctures from hedge
cuttings are common.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Having ridden it for a couple of months the freewheel packed up about
5 miles from home. I had to call out International Rescue and put the
bike in the boot of the car. Decathlon didn't have any freewheels in
stock, so gave me a complete new wheel. Definitely excellent customer
service. They showed me the broken freewheel which had rusted and the
bearings were badly worn on the drive side. I wash my bike after every
ride in the winter and am careful not to get detergent or GT85
anywhere near bearings.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Rear cassette after 1500 miles&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2015-03_triban/IMG_20150224_164314.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Rear cassette after 1500 miles"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2015-03_triban/IMG_20150224_164314.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
After 1500 miles the gears began to skip. Measuring the chain it didn't appear
unduly worn. However, the teeth on the cassette looked just like
sharks teeth! My LBS replaced the cassette and chain, plus the cables.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So what's the final verdict. Overall I am happy with the Triban. I
enjoy riding it and I don't worry too much it getting plastered in
muck and grit. For the price it's a good buy, but don't expect the
drive chain to be as durable as a more expensive bike.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cycling</category><category>review</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2015-03-02-decathlon-triban-500SE/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2015 17:59:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Alpkit Brupot</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-10-06-Alpkit%20BruPot/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I prefer gas for cooking and my stove of choice is the Primus
Gravity. This is a remote canister stove, with a pre-heater, which
makes it suitable for use in colder weather. Almost all my camping
cooking is just a matter of boiling water to make a hot drink, or
prepare a freeze dried meal.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I have looked at Jetboil stoves, but decided that they weren't for me
because they were too heavy and the long tall shape makes them
potentially unstable. However, if I needed to melt snow they would
probably be my primary choice. One thing I haven't seen other
manufacturers make is a cooking pot with a heat exchanger on the
bottom, which could potentially improve the performance of a normal
gas stove. However, &lt;a href="https://www.alpkit.com/products/brupot"&gt;Alpkit&lt;/a&gt; have now made a cooking pot with built in
heat exchanger. I decided to buy one with the hope that it would
reduce the time it takes to boil water on my stove and potentially
save gas.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Alpkit BruPot test setup&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-10-Brukit/IMG_20141004_160215.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Alpkit BruPot test setup"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-10-Brukit/IMG_20141004_160215.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
The Brupot was delivered with the typical rapid efficiency. I wanted
to compare it to my MSR stainless steel kettle, which is my usual
cooking pot. Both vessels hold 1 litre of liquid, but the Brupot is
slightly slimmer and therefore narrower. The Brupot has a plastic detachable
lid, with a drinking slot so you can use it as a cup. It has
detachable handles, which are covered in plastic so you don't burn
your hands. There is a tightly fitting neoprene sleeve, which acts as
a pot cosy. However, Alpkit recommends that you remove this when
cooking. Since the sleeve is a tight fit, it's effectively
useless. Can you image trying to fit a tight sleeve round a pot full
of boiling water without burning your hands?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Alpkit BruPot and MSR kettle." href="/images/2014-10-Brukit/IMG&lt;sub&gt;20141006&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;165911.jpg&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Alpkit BruPot and MSR kettle." title="Alpkit BruPot and MSR kettle." src="/images/2014-10-Brukit/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;20141006&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;165911.jpg&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I decided to do a head to head to see how long each pot would take to
boil 500ml of water. I used my Primus stove with a full 500g
canister. The test was conducted in the kitchen, so I didn't bother
using a wind shield. I adjusted the flame on the stove so it didn't
come round the sides of the pot and I didn't alter the flame setting when
I swapped the pans. Each pan was filled with 500ml of cold water from
the tap and placed on the stove.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I measured the time it took a continuous jet of steam to appear, which
should correspond to a rolling boil. I didn't take the top off either
pan off while it was heating the water, as this would increase the
time to get a rolling boil. Thus there may have been a small error in
judging when a pot was actually boiling. Also I didn't conduct another
test with no lids on the pots, which would have made it easier to see
if there was a rolling boil, as this isn't the way I use the pot when
camping. I repeated the test three times. Between each set of repeat experiments
I turned off the gas, then re-lit the stove , so the times for each
run can't be summed to give an average, as the gas flow was probably
different for each run.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Much to my surprise the Alpkit BruPot was slower to reach a rolling
boil than the MSR, by about ten seconds in each test. That's not a big
difference, but I was expecting the BruPot to be significantly faster
because of the heat exchanger. I like the BruPot and it will probably
replace my MSR kettle, because the handles and top are
better. However, it seems that the heat exchanger doesn't work for my
use case.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The Alpkit Brupot weighs 266g, including the bag and my MSR kettle
weighs 254g.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org21686ba" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org21686ba"&gt;&lt;span class="timestamp-wrapper"&gt;&lt;span class="timestamp"&gt;[2014-10-07 Tue] &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Update.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org21686ba"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was pointed out to me that I really should also be measuring the
weight of gas used. In my original experiment I didn't weight the gas
canister. I believe my conclusions were valid as I didn't alter the
gas flow between swapping pots and I was starting with a full 500g
canister, so I would have expected flow to remain almost constant, so
the weight of gas consumed would be the same. Also in the second run I
swapped the order of the pots in the test, which should have shown up
any differences caused by changes in gas flow between tests. In both
cases the MSR boiled faster.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
However, in the interests of accuracy I repeated my experiment and
weighed the gas canister at the beginiing and end of each test.The
first time I did this I kept the canister attached to the stove and
stood the canister on top of the scales. I didn't alter the setting of
the valve between pots, but did note the weight of the canister before
and after the pot boiled. I did two separate runs, restarting the
stove for each run.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Water was from the cold tap, which was allowed to flow for a couple of
minutes first, so all the water used shuld have had the same starting temperature.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Whilst I believe that the boil &lt;b&gt;times&lt;/b&gt; are comparable within each run,
the effect of the hose attached to the top of the canister meant that
the &lt;b&gt;weights&lt;/b&gt; probably were not accurate. So, I repeated the whole
thing again, but this time removed the gas canister from the pipe
before weighing it. Since when I re-lighted the stove, I couldn't be
certain that I was using the same flow rate I believe that the &lt;b&gt;times&lt;/b&gt;
for this set of results are not comparable, but the &lt;b&gt;weight of gas&lt;/b&gt;
consumed is.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org4cf28a9" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="org4cf28a9"&gt;Gas Cylinder Removed Before Weighing.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-org4cf28a9"&gt;
&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="all" frame="border"&gt;
&lt;caption class="t-above"&gt;&lt;span class="table-number"&gt;Table 1:&lt;/span&gt; Alpkit BruPot.&lt;/caption&gt;

&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Start Weight&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;End Weight&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Gas Used&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Time to boil&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;513&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;501&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;4:26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;493&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;480&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;3:54&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="all" frame="border"&gt;
&lt;caption class="t-above"&gt;&lt;span class="table-number"&gt;Table 2:&lt;/span&gt; MSR Kettle.&lt;/caption&gt;

&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Start Weight&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;End Weight&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Gas Used&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Time to boil&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;501&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;493&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;4:12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;480&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;469&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;3:20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org00a903a" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="org00a903a"&gt;Gas Cylinder Weighed Without Removing From Flexible Pipe.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-org00a903a"&gt;
&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="all" frame="border"&gt;
&lt;caption class="t-above"&gt;&lt;span class="table-number"&gt;Table 3:&lt;/span&gt; First Run.&lt;/caption&gt;

&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Pot&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Start Weight&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;End Weight&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Gas Used&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Time to boil&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Alpkit&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;599&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;584&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;4:09&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;MSR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;545&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;534&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;3:30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="all" frame="border"&gt;
&lt;caption class="t-above"&gt;&lt;span class="table-number"&gt;Table 4:&lt;/span&gt; Second Run.&lt;/caption&gt;

&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Pot&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Start Weight&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;End Weight&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Gas Used&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Time Time to boil&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Alpkit&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;572&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;555&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;3:52&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;MSR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;583&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;573&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;3:31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org88b0770" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org88b0770"&gt;Conclusions.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org88b0770"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The difference in performance between the BruPot and the MSR kettle
are quite small and probably have little effect in real world use. The
only real surprise is that in my setup the hest exchanger doesn't seem
to have any positive effect. However, I still like the Alpkit BruPot
and one advantage over my MSR is I can fit a 200g gas canister inside
it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>review</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-10-06-Alpkit%20BruPot/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 17:58:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Time Lapse Photography</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-10-01-Time-Lapse-Photography/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
A couple of years ago my son wanted to do a photography project for
school. We had recently bought a Canon EOS 550D DSLR, which he was
keen to use. While wasting time browsing various photography sites, I
found several references to using the Canon for making time lapse
films. The basic concept is that you take a sequence of still photos
over several hours and then combine them together into a video
format. Thus you can condense many hours of still photography into a
short video, which shows a speeded up version of the scene you
photographed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org6c06a5c" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org6c06a5c"&gt;Equipment.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org6c06a5c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Certain types of photography are well suited to making time
lapses. Astro-photography and landscapes are a couple of obvious
candidates. Apart from a suitable camera, you need a few additional
bits of equipment:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A decent tripod. The camera must not move between shots and will
need to be in the same spot for as long as the time lapse
lasts. This can vary from a couple of hours to a whole 24hrs, or more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An intervalometer (see below). Not essential, but makes life much easier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of patience. You can be standing around for hours in the cold
and initially you will probably experience many frustrating
failures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org13912e5" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org13912e5"&gt;Battery Life.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org13912e5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you are going for a long sequence consider getting an extended
battery pack. If the temperature is low your battery life will be
considerably reduced. You might want to try warming your battery pack,
but this can also cause condensation on the lens!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orga4af7fd" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orga4af7fd"&gt;Intervalometers.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orga4af7fd"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can trigger the shutter of  a Canon either from a PC via its usb
port, or by using something like a RaspberryPi.  See:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
However, for outside work this is very inconvenient and prone to
failure. It's far better to use an intervalometer. The basic functions
are:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delay: the amount of time between pressing "Start" and when the
first picture is taken.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interval: the time between which photos are taken. If you set this to
one minute a photo will be taken every minute.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Long: The amount of time the shutter is left open.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Number: the number of photos you want the intervalometer to take.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are a lot of these around. Here is an example on &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Ramozz-intervalometer-remote-shutter-Camera/dp/B00C1C0WQC/ref=sr_1_1?s=electronics&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1412174972&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=intervalometer"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;. They
all seems to be made in the same Chinese factory. Try Googling
"Hongdak MC-36B". The cost is £10 upwards depending on who you buy it
from. If you are serious about time lapse photos buying one of these
will save you endless hours of frustration. Note different models
support different cameras. Make sure you buy the right one for your
camera! There is a good review of the Hongdak &lt;a href="http://www.linearconcepts.com/photography/reviews/photo1"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org3606c24" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org3606c24"&gt;Alternatives to Using a DSLR.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org3606c24"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Note that neither the Pi, nor the GoPro are suitable to taking photos
of stars, although the rumoured GpPro4 is meant to fix that problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org8edd616" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="org8edd616"&gt;Raspberry Pi.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-org8edd616"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Definitely a geek solution. Relatively cheap when bought with a
camera.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are a couple of dedicated cases suitable for outdoor use, but
a real geek will use a Tupperware box.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can use a rechargeable battery  and its low power consumption
means it will continue working for a long period.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Camera is surprisingly good, but definitely not up to DSLR standards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Disadvantages:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are working outside there is no easy method of getting a
preview of what the camera can see. It's possible to bodge this by
making the Pi into a WiFi hotspot and using your phone to view the
photos it has taken. However, not very practical, except for the
real hard core geek.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org0e37108" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="org0e37108"&gt;GoPro.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-org0e37108"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why use a GoPro?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's very light. Important if you are carrying it up a big mountain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It comes in a waterproof case, so you can safely leave it outside
without worrying about it getting soaked.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are innumerable fixings and brackets available. You can easily
attach it to something like a walking pole as a tripod.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you get fed up of time lapses you can use it to film your wing
suit &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WRqnTODwvEA"&gt;jump&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has reasonably comprehensive time lapse facilities built in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Controllable from your smart phone or via a WiFi dongle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some disadvantages:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Short battery life. Around 2hrs in optimal conditions, although you
can get extended battery packs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not suitable for photographing stars, although general low light
performance is good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limited exposure control and a fixed wide angle lens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org5768425" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org5768425"&gt;Night Time Photography (Stars and Star Trails).&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org5768425"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The factors to consider are the ISO setting and length of exposure. If
you set the ISO too high, the camera sensor will produce a lot of
noise and degrade the image. If you set the exposure to be too long,
the stars will move while the photograph is being exposed, leading to
blurred images.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Make sure you turn auto-focus off. The infinity setting on your lens
is probably not going to give you a sharp image. Make sure you focus
manually. I tend to use an aperture of around F5.6, but this will
depend on your lens. Generally using your lens's widest aperture won't
give you the best results.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Set your white balance to around 3500K. This helps to reduce redness
from any sodium lighting that is around and will give you a blue
sky. If you leave your shutter open to log, you will get star trails,
as the stars move across the sky during the exposure because of the
earth's rotation. To avoid star trails limit your exposure to
1000/focal length.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you want to capture star trails, take multiple exposures over a few
hours. You can the "stack" the multiple images to produce
trails. There are several applications for Linux:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.markus-enzweiler.de/software/software.html"&gt;StarStaX&lt;/a&gt; by Markus Enzweiler&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href="http://linuxdarkroom.tassy.net/star-trail-image-stacking/"&gt;scripted&lt;/a&gt; method for using GIMP.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you are in the northern hemisphere you will get the best trail
effect by pointing your camera towards the north. The pole start
appears fixed in position, so if your camera is pointing towards it
the stars will form trails centred around the pole star.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You may also want to take a dark frame. Simply put a lens cap on and
take a photograph using the same settings you use for taking the star
trails. You can use the dark frame later on as a method of removing
background noise from your photographs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf6a74e2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgf6a74e2"&gt;Landscapes.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgf6a74e2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I live in the countryside and am a keen mountaineer, so have lots of
opportunities for landscape photography. One of the key requirements
is to identify suitable spots to take time lapses in
advance. Sunrise/sunsets are a good place to start. However, you need
to know where the sun will be when it sets/rises and be in the right
location to record the event. Usually a clear view of the horizon, or
some definitive feature e.g. a mountain.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Often success/failure will depend on the weather. The best
landscape conditions are often in the clear atmospheres of autumn, winter
and spring, when haze is minimal. Some clouds in the sky add interest,
as they will move during the period of your filming. Be prepared for
frequent disappointments. Often cloud will be too extensive, or the
mist will descend at an inconvenient moment.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's particularly important to let your equipment equilibrate to the
ambient temperature. If you don't do this you will almost certainly
get condensation on the lens, which will ruin all your efforts. Allow
around 30 mins for the temperature of the camera to
equilibrate. Sometimes there is so much humidity that you will get
condensation anyway. This can often happen when it's cold.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org1ea252d" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org1ea252d"&gt;Software.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org1ea252d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So you have had a successful filming expedition and now have hundreds
of JPG's you want to convert into a Hollywood Epic. There are many
tools available, but I use ffmpeg and mencoder.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
ffmpeg is correctly known as the Swiss army knife of video
manipulation. It is in perpetual beta, the command line options get
changed on the developer's whim and it can probably even make the
tea. There are a whole raft of video conversion options. I freely
admit that I don't understand most of them, but I'll try and explain
why I chose the ones I use.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First you need to check that your JPG's are numbered sequentially. If
they aren't I'll leave you to write a script that renames them. In the
case of the GoPro file names look like: G0040383. Now ffmpeg has a
very useful option: start&lt;sub&gt;number&lt;/sub&gt; that will start at the file you name
and process all the files in the directory with sequential
numbers. However, if there is a gap in the numbers it will grind to a
halt. Even better ffmpeg understands shell globs, so:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;ffmpeg -f image2 -start_number &lt;span class="m"&gt;91495&lt;/span&gt; -i G00%d.JPG
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
will process all the files in the directory that start with "G00"
beginning with "G0091495".
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Almost all of my ffmpeg options are taken from &lt;a href="http://blog.waan.name/creating-timelapse-videos-on-linux/"&gt;waan's&lt;/a&gt; site.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So my full command line looks like:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;ffmpeg -f image2 -start_number &lt;span class="m"&gt;91495&lt;/span&gt; -i G00%d.JPG  -r &lt;span class="m"&gt;25&lt;/span&gt; -s 1280x960 -vcodec libx264 -b:v 30000k timelapse_25fps.mp4
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This creates a video of 25 frames per second using an h264 codec. If
your time lapse seems to be going too quickly, you can adjust the
speed using mencoder:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;mencoder -speed &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;.25 -ofps &lt;span class="m"&gt;25&lt;/span&gt; -ovc copy timelapse_25fps.mp4 -o quarter_speed.mp4
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The above command will slow things down to a quarter of the original speed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So now you have the perfect time lapse video and you want to spice it
up by adding an audio track. I am assuming that you already have a
suitable mp3 to hand. There will almost inevitably be a mismatch in
the duration of the mp3 file and the video. If the mp3 is too long you
can trim it to the length of the video when you multiplex the file:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;ffmpeg -i timelapse.mp4 -i music.mp3 -map &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;:0 -map &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;:0 -codec copy  -shortest output_video.mp4
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If the mp3 file is too short you can create a loop that is longer than
the video (thanks to StackExchange for this):
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sox -e ima-adpcm short_audio.mp3 looped_audio.mp3 repeat &lt;span class="m"&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# adjust count as necessary&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now use the shortest option with ffmpeg to multiplex the tracks, as
per the instructions above.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orga0be893" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orga0be893"&gt;Some of My Time Lapse Videos.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orga0be893"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have uploaded several time lapses to YouTube. These are all quite
short and only intended to show you the sort of effects you can achieve:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gsb9mcleTiQ"&gt;Cwm Eigiau&lt;/a&gt; sunrise from the slopes of Carnedd Llewelyn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zcIY-HQZZuc"&gt;Sunset&lt;/a&gt; taken with the Canon DSLR.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bEg3jMXT7wM"&gt;Sunset&lt;/a&gt; taken using a GoPro.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iUoGD5vXpXY"&gt;Stars&lt;/a&gt; time lapse taken using the Canon DSLR.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mleropQkFTk"&gt;Dawn to dusk&lt;/a&gt; time lapse taken using a Raspberry Pi.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>photography</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-10-01-Time-Lapse-Photography/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 17:58:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Cwm Eigiau Backpack</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-09-11-cwm-eigiau-backpack/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org4591668" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org4591668"&gt;Day One Llyn Eigiau to Carnedd Llewelyn .&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org4591668"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The summer weather looked set to continue for at least a few more
days, so I decided to have another go at the walk that I had done in
July. On the last trip I had forgotten my stove, so had to complete
the whole walk in a very long ten hour day. his time I was planning to
climb Pen Llithrigg yr Wrach and traverse the ridge over Pen yr Helgi
Du and Craig yr Ysfa to a camp site a couple of hundred feet below the
summit of Carnedd Llewelyn.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;A hazy Carnedd Llewelyn  from Pen Llithrig yr Wrach&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-09-carned/IMG_8813.JPG" class="rounded
float-left" alt="A hazy Carnedd Llewelyn  from Pen Llithrig yr Wrach"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-09-carned/IMG_8813.JPG"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I didn't leave home until mid-morning. When I arrived at the start of
the road up into Cwm Eigiau there were signs at the bottom of the road
warning of long delays. Luckily I wasn't held up by what turned out to
be fairly minor repairs. It was midweek, so there were only about
three cars in the car park when I pulled in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Although it was hot, the heat had made the atmosphere hazy and some of
the summits were obscured by mist. I double checked all my gear before
setting off to make sure that I hadn't forgotten something important
like the stove. Feeling confident that I hadn't forgotten anything I
set off along the track towards the reservoir. After about half a mile
I realized that I hadn't turned the GPS on! I seldom use the GPS for
navigation, but like to keep a record of my track.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Mist over Tryfan and the Glyders&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-09-carned/IMG_8817.JPG" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Mist over Tryfan and the Glyders"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-09-carned/IMG_8817.JPG"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
I filled my 2 litre and 1 litre Platypus water bottles from the
reservoir and also the Travel Tap. I wasn't sure if this would be
enough, but it turned out towards the just about the right amount, as
I had about 500ml spare in the morning for the walk back. There are
not really any water sources on top of the Carneddau, except for some
stagnant peaty pools. In the past I have used water from these and
filtered it through the Travel Tap. I don't normally bother filtering
the water from the reservoir.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
Plodding along the track I soon reached the old quarry workings at ???
and stopped for a rest. For the first time I had brought the GoPro
video camera with me, so I made a couple of short videos of the
view. The path beyond the quarry is vague, so I headed up diagonally
towards the ridge. Sweating in the heat, I finally found the path
along the crest of the ridge that leads up to the summit of Pen
Llithrig yr Wrach.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On my last trip I had started to get cramp on the pull up to Pen yr
Helgi Du and wanted to avoid it this time. I stopped for a rest, drank
quite a lot of water and ate a couple of flapjacks.  Moel Siabod was
only just visible through the haze and the tops of Tryfan and the
Glyders were covered in mist. While I was resting on the summit a man
appeared up the slope from Pen yr Helgi Du. While chatting to him we
heard a Chough calling. I said that had seen several Grouse lower
down. Apparently Grouse numbers have dropped considerably since the
1970's when the moors were managed.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Craig yr Ysfa and Pen yr Helgi Du at sunset&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-09-carned/IMG_8818.JPG" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Craig yr Ysfa and Pen yr Helgi Du at sunset"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-09-carned/IMG_8818.JPG"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
I dropped down to the col between Pen Llithrig yr Wrach and Pen yr
Helgi Du. The slope up to the summit of Pen yr Helgi Du didn't seem
too bad this time and I didn't get cramp in my legs. I walked along
the summit ridge and began the descent of the ??? ridge. It was here
that I met the only other person I saw all day. I stopped to let him
pass as he climbed towards the summit. The scramble down is quite
steep, but fairly short. If you don't like exposure, make sure that
you keep to the left (facing out). I was soon down at Bwlch Eryl
Farchog and began the climb towards Craig yr Ysfa. The atmosphere was
beginning to clear and the views were improving as evening began to
draw in. The short scramble up the rocky step was awkward with a heavy
sack, but I was soon standing on the summit of Craig yr Ysfa. I had a
quick look over the top at the pinaccles near the top of Amphitheatre
Buttress. I have done this climb several times in the past and it's
one of the best long mountaineering routes in Wales. The climbing is
easy apart from the short crux section. If you can jam, climbing the
crack to the top of a short wall is easy. There is then a very exposed
step right onto a small ledge. Faling off here would involve a long
fall into the gulley below. However, you can drop a long sling over a
pinnacle, which protects the step round and the ground above is
easier. The final section of easy climbing over the pinaccles is a
delightfully exposed scramble. Maybe next time I'll climb up from
Ogwen, dump my sack on the top, descend to the bottom, the climb back
up to my sack and camp on Carnedd Llewelyn.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was now around 5:30, so I decided to camp on the
flat grassy shelf on the SE ridge of Carnedd Llewelyn that I had used
a couple of times in the past:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
 The site is quite sheltered and there
are several piles of rock nearby, which are useful tables. It's quite
near to the main path up Carnedd Llewelyn, but far enough away that
you are not likely to be noticed by people passing by. It was now
shortly after 6:00pm and there was nobody else visible anywhere on the
Carneddau. The site is a bit tussocky, but I had soon found a nice
flat area to pitch the tent. I pitched it with the door facing East,
overlooking Cwm Eigiau so I could see the dawn from the tent door.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I soon had the stove going and boiled enough water to make a hot
chocolate and re-hydrate a Bewell Chilli. Despite sitting in a pot
cosy for 10 minutes, the rice in the chilli didn't seem to have
rehydrated properly. I boiled some more water, poured it into the
pouch and waited another 5 minutes. The rice still didn't seem to be
properly cooked, but I ate it anyway. I was tired so after taking a
few photos I got into my sleeping bag. After a short rest, I got out
of the tent to set up the GoPro. I wanted to take a series of still
photos of the dawn at intervals of 30 seconds and then turn these into
a video of the sunrise. I spent some time fiddling around with the
various GoPro brackets that I had brought with me and eventually
managed to rig up something that locked to my walking pole. There then
followed a short pantomime, while I tried to find a spot in the grass
where I could push the walking into. Finding somewhere that didn't
have a rock a few inches under the ground proved difficult. When I had
found a good spot I set the GoPro up facing over Cwm Eigiau and then
retired to bed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Carnedd Llewelyn campsite at sunset&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-09-carned/IMG_8836.JPG" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Carnedd Llewelyn campsite at sunset"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-09-carned/IMG_8836.JPG"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
The GoPro is in a weather proof case, so if it rained it didn't
matter. Keeping it inside the tent isn't a good idea, as it's warmer
inside the tent than outside, or at least it should be! Taking the
camera from a warm tent to a cold outside usually results on
condensation on the lens which spoils your photos.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org7ca03fa" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org7ca03fa"&gt;Day Two - Return Via Gledrffordd.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org7ca03fa"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The battery life of a GoPro in time lapse mode is around two hours. It
was quite cold at 3000 feet, so I expected the battery life to be
shorter. I set an alarm for 5:30am, so I could turn the GoPro on to
start taking the time lapse photos some time before the sun came over
the horizon . I woke up before the alarm went off and the Eastern sky
was already beginning to glow red. I scrambled out of the tent and set
the GoPro off. I made myself a hot drink while I watched the horizon
as it gradually got lighter and the sun finally appeared. Unlike the
previous day the atmosphere was crystal clear and the summits were
clear of mist. However, by about 7:00am mist had drifted over from the
west and all the views were obscured.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="" height="" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Gsb9mcleTiQ?rel=0&amp;amp;hd=1&amp;amp;wmode=transparent"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I packed away and began the trudge up towards the summit of Carnedd
Llewelyn. I could see patches of blue above me, but all the views were
obscured. From the summit, I set off along the ridge heading towards
Foel Grach. I began descending and was about to get the map out to
check my position, when I dropped below the mist. I could now see the
path that descends to Gledrffordd. I thought about continuing over to
Foel Grach and then descending the ridge that leads from the summit down to Gledrffordd,
but the mist was coming and going over the summit. I didn't want to
walk all the way up to the summit only to find the view obscured by the mist.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tent at dawn. Mist rolling in.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-09-carned/IMG_8850.JPG" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Tent at dawn. Mist rolling in."&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-09-carned/IMG_8850.JPG"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
The descent was straightforward and this time I didn't make the
mistake of climbing onto the top of Craig Eigiau, but contoured along
below the ridge. As I joined the Landrover track I met what appeared
to be a school party who were being shown how to find where they were
on the map by their teacher.  Further along the track I passed a man
and what appeared to be his daughter heading up the track. When I
reached the car park there were only two or three other cars parked
there. Being able to walk midweek is definitely and advantage if you
want the hills to yourself.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>mountaineering</category><category>tripreport</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-09-11-cwm-eigiau-backpack/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2014 17:58:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>C2c Prologue</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-08-24-C2C-Prologue/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
There are a number of Coast to Coast cycle rides in the UK. This
series of posts is about the ride that starts at either Workington or
Whitehaven and finishes at Tynemouth or Sunderland. Depending on the
route you choose the ride is around 140 miles long with approximately
15,000 ft (altitude calculated from my GPS tracks) of ascent. We had
decided to do the ride over three days.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There were five of us planning to do the ride: my son with two of his
friends and one of my brothers in law. My brother in law could only
join us for the last two days. Also I wanted to let my son ride in a
group with his friends, without having his ancient Dad tagging
along. This meant that I  was effectively riding solo,  since I
do almost all my cycling alone this suited me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had done the Way of the Roses last year on my hybrid bike. I had
carried a fair bit of gear in panniers. For the C2C I decided to use
my road bike and carry a minimal amount of gear in a rucksack. Most
cyclists don't like carrying a rucksack, but since I do a lot of
walking and climbing, I find I prefer to carry things in a rucksack
rather than in panniers. As I was using my road bike, I made a couple
of modifications to the "Official Route". On the descent from
Whinatter I followed the road, rather than the track through the
forest. Leaving Keswick I cycled past Castlerigg Stone circles before
rejoining the C2C at Threlkeld, thus avoiding the railway track. On
day three I avoided cycling along the Waskerley Way, taking the B road
that runs parallel to it. However, my son, who was also on his road
bike cycled, along the Waskerley Way and said it was fine.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Depending on the route you take the C2C is around 140 miles long with
approximately 16,600ft (5,320 metres) of ascent. Most people do the
route over several days. We had decided to do it in three days. Day
one was Whitehaven to Keswick. We chose Keswick as the destination
because my son and his friends were staying at one of his friend's
grandmother's house. This turned out to be a good choice as the ride
wasn't too hard, so was a nice introduction to the route.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Day two was Keswick to Allenheads. I chose the destination on the
basis that it Allenheads was supposed to be the end of the big hills,
so day three would be a nice easy ride. This turned out to be quite a
short day and it turned out that there were two more big hills beyond
Allenheads!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Day three was Allenheads to Tynemouth/Sunderland. My son and his
friends had chosen to finish at Sunderland where one of his friends
parents was going to pick them up an drive them home. My brother in
law and I planned to finish at Tynemouth. However, I had to get back
to Whitehaven and then drive four hours to get home, as we were going
on holiday the next day. My brother in law had done the route
previously and knew that we couldn't take cycles on the metro, so
would have to cycle the ten miles from Tynemouth back to Newcastle
station. I wasn't that bothered about going all the way to the coast,
so we finished at Newcastle station.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
See my rant about rail transport arrangements for the C2C.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf7e78df" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgf7e78df"&gt;Accomodation.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgf7e78df"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd5c4530" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgd5c4530"&gt;Day 0 (Pre-ride).&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgd5c4530"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We drove up the day before our first stage. My son and his friends
stayed at the The Waverley Hotel hotel in Whitehaven, whilst I stayed
at &lt;a href="http://www.chestnuts-whitehaven.com"&gt;Chestnuts&lt;/a&gt; about three miles outside Whitehaven. If you like animals
I can thoroughly recommend Chestnuts. The owners are very helpful and
accommodating. The B&amp;amp;B is comfortable and the breakfasts good and they
will serve you an early breakfast if you want an early start. The
owners run a small animal sanctuary, in addition to having several
pets of their own. There are dogs, cats, chinchillas, a parrot and
some owls.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc179098" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgc179098"&gt;Day 1 - Keswick.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgc179098"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I stayed in the Travelodge on the A66, just outside Keswick. This can
be reached by following a cycle path from the roundabout complex over
the M6. This Travelodge has recently been renovated and the rooms seem
better than the average Travelodge. Don't rely on the Little Chef
opening at 7:00am, as it claims. There is a notice stuck to the door
saying it opens at 8:00am. However, Morrisons serve good and cheap breakfasts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org339606b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org339606b"&gt;Day 2 - Allenheads.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org339606b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I stayed at &lt;a href="http://www.allenheadsc2c.com"&gt;Newhouses&lt;/a&gt; which is a very comfortable B&amp;amp;B just on the edge
of the village, up a steep stone track. This was very comfortable with
a residents lounge and an excellent breakfast. My son and his friends
stayed at the ???, which they said was fine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org90b6a5d" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org90b6a5d"&gt;Useful Books and Web Sites.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org90b6a5d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I found the &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/C2C-Cycle-Route-Cicerone-Guides-ebook/dp/B00A2MKYO8/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1411372919&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=c2c+cicerone"&gt;Cicerone&lt;/a&gt; guide a great source of information before and
during the ride. I decided to buy the Kindle version. For me the only
disadvantage of the Kindle version was that the maps aren't zoomable,
so are basically unreadable on a small screen. However since I had a
paper map this didn't matter to me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;a href="http://www.c2c-guide.co.uk/"&gt;C2C&lt;/a&gt; web site is the official resource for the ride and contains
lots of information.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org1081b9d" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org1081b9d"&gt;Map.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org1081b9d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Although the route is very well signposted, carrying a map is highly
recommended. I used the &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1901389650/ref=pd_lpo_sbs_dp_ss_1?pf_rd_p=479289247&amp;amp;pf_rd_s=lpo-top-stripe&amp;amp;pf_rd_t=201&amp;amp;pf_rd_i=1852846496&amp;amp;pf_rd_m=A3P5ROKL5A1OLE&amp;amp;pf_rd_r=1YC5Z8C9KDRGP64NK2R6"&gt;Sustrans&lt;/a&gt; official map. The map shows both on
road and off road alternatives. It was well worth buying. However,
there are a couple of minor niggles:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no grid lines, which makes it hard to cross reference your
position using a GPS or OS map.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In order to fit all the ride onto one map, it only shows a narrow
strip. Thus it's hard to see places of interest, or route
alternatives without referring to another map.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Despite these minor niggles, I would recommend that you buy the map.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org75ebcda" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org75ebcda"&gt;Ride Statistics.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org75ebcda"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Times are taken from my GPS logs. The exclude major stops at
cafes. However, they do include minor stops such as 30min or so  to
fix a puncture outside Keswick. Altitudes and distances are taken
directly from the GPS log.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The initial section of day two doesn't include the steep climb from
the centre of Penrith up to Beacon Edge because I forgot to start the
GPS and I wasn't about to drop back down the hill and cycle up it again!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In retrospect if I did the ride again, I would go further on the
second day, or do the whole thing in two days. My brother in law had
previously done the ride in two days, going from Whitehaven to
Allenheads in one day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgef95aa4" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgef95aa4"&gt;Day One.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgef95aa4"&gt;
&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="hsides"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Whitehaven to Penrith&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Distance miles/km&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Ascent ft/metres&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Total Time&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;3 hrs 10 min (includes fix puncture) to Keswick&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;54.6 (87.4)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;5961 (1834)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;5:40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;2 hrs 30 min to Penrith&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org28f0953" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org28f0953"&gt;Day Two.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org28f0953"&gt;
&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="hsides"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Penrith to Allenheads&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Distance miles/km&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Ascent ft/metres&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Time&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Penrith to Hartside Cross (cafe) 1hr 53 min&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;33.6 (53.8)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;5177 (1593)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;3:57&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Hartside to Allenheads 2hr 4min&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org953401b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org953401b"&gt;Day Three.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org953401b"&gt;
&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="hsides"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Allenheads to Newcastle&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Distance miles/km&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Ascent ft/metres&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Time&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;4hrs 33mins&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;44.3 (70.9)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;3569 (1098)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;4:33&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc58b29d" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgc58b29d"&gt;Train Rant!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgc58b29d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had hope to do the ride without needing to use the car. Getting from
Crewe to Whitehaven with a bike didn't seem too problematic, although
bikes have to be pre-booked and the number of spaces aren't known
until you try to make your booking. However, getting back from
Tynemouth to Whitehaven was a different matter. I discovered from my
brother in law, who had done the ride before, that you can't take
cycles on the metro from Tynemouth back into the centre of Newcastle.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once back in Newcastle, you have to catch a train to Carlisle, then
another one to Whitehaven. At present both services are run by
Northern Rail. Their web site promises:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Northern is strongly committed to promoting cycling as a sustainable
and healthy means of transport that complements our train service. Our
vision is to 'connect people to opportunities by the most sustainable
means' and cycling has an important role to play. We want to do more
to make this an attractive option so we are working with local
authorities and the cycling community to see where we can make our
stations more cycle-friendly.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Bikes are carried free of charge at any time and you don't need to make reservations.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The cycle space on trains is clearly marked, both internally and
externally. Space is allocated on a first come, first served basis.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We can only carry a maximum of two bikes per train but conductors have
responsibility for the safety of their train and have the right to
refuse entry if the train is busy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Note that bikes can't be pre-booked and there are only two spaces per
train. So after a three day ride, you don't know if you can actually
get your bike on a train. The C2C is one of the most popular long
distance cycle routes in England, with hundreds of people completing
it each year. The provision of two bike spaces per train is derisory!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In practice the train from Newcastle to Carlisle had more spaces
(probably around 6). However, the Carlisle to Whitehaven service did
only have two spaces. Luckily the conductor was happy to let extra
bikes onto the train. We could just as easily have been unlucky and
had to wait for possibly days for a space. It's not as though
installing extra spaces is expensive, or complicated. Also it has
minimal impact on the total number of passengers that can be carried.
So Northern Rail how about living up to your grand "Mission Statement"
and actually provide a proper cycle carriage service.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cycling</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-08-24-C2C-Prologue/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2014 17:58:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>C2c Day Two</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-08-23-C2C-Day-Two/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Le Grand Depart&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140813_090832.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Le Grand Depart"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140813_090832.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
We had originally planned this section to complete the major climbs of
the middle section in one day. It turned out to be a very short day,
about three and a half hours (excluding tops). In retrospect it would have been better
to continue beyond Allenheads, but as we had pre-booked accomodation
this wasn't possible. With a bit more planning we could have probably
completed the route in two days, although for me, this would have been
pushing it a bit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We had arranged to meet my son and his friends at the place they were
staying in Penrith about 8:30am. We had planned to have breakfast at
the Little Chef, but although the pillar on the outside said it would
open at 7:00am, it turned out that it wouldn't in fact open until
8:00am. Somewhat fed up, I decided to cycle down into Penrith and have
breakfast at Morrisons. After breakfast, I cycled up the steep hill to
the house where my son was staying. The house was actually on the C2C,
which made initial route finding straightforward.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My son and his friends raced off in front while my brother in law and
myself followed at a more sedate pace. Once again the weather looked
decidedly dodgy, with cloud obscuring the moors in front of us. We
passed through Langwathby . There followed several sections of up and
down, but nothing too steep. We could see cars climbing the A686, high
up on the moors, in the distance. The tops were covered in cloud, so
we couldn't see that cafe.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Looking back from Hartside cafe&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140813_105959.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Looking back from Hartside cafe"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140813_105959.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
From the description I had expected the hill up to Hartside to be
challenging. However, it turned out to be much easier than many of the
other lesser hills. It's long, but apart from a very short section,
where the route joins the main A686, it's not particularly steep. I
managed to maintain a respectable pace and only stopped to take
photos. I arrived at the cafe just as the cloud lifted. I couldn't
have timed it better. The cafe wasn't too busy and a couple of cups of
tea with an apricot slice were very welcome.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The descent from the cafe was very pleasant. Although it's on an A
road, there was very little traffic. Not having seen any traffic for
the last three miles, as soon as I wanted to turn right at Leadgate a
veritable convoy suddenly appeared behind me. The ride down into
Garigill was pleasant. However, the initial section out of there was a
shocker. After overcoming the very steep start, the hill goes
on, and on, and on. However, the subsequent sections aren't too steep and there
are fine views all around. We stopped for a drink and some food at the
top of the hill before beginning the descent towards Nenthead. Just
before arriving at Nenthead there is a very steep descent. This
culminates in a couple of very sharp bends and the road is very
potholed. There are several signs warning you to slow down. Take note!
Going too fast will result in a painful crash.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Crossing into Northumberland&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140813_130528.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Crossing into Northumberland"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/IMG_20140813_130528.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
My wife was waiting at Nenthead and we stopped for a chat and some
more to drink.  After an initial steep climb out of the village we
turned off along the B road to climb up to the top of Black Hill, the
highest point of the C2C. There follows a short descent before another
small hill. After that it's a great downhill ride all the way to
Allenheads.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;View from above Nenthead&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140813_130640.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="View from above Nenthead"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140813_130640.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
The village of Allenheads is quite stretched out and the pub and our
accommodation were at the far end. My son and his friends stayed in
the pub,  ee stayed at &lt;a href="http://www.allenheadsc2c.com"&gt;Newhouses&lt;/a&gt;, which was a
short way out of the village up a track. The proprietor seemed very
confused about exactly who she had booked in, despite email
confirmations. However, we sorted it out eventually. The accommodation
was superb. The rooms were large and comfortable. Downstairs there was
a separate residents lounge and kitchen.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After a short rest, we wandered down into the village to join the
others at the pub. We had an enjoyable meal and a few drinks before
wandering back up the road to our beds.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cycling</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-08-23-C2C-Day-Two/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2014 17:58:18 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>