<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ian's Blog. (Posts about book)</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/categories/book.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:ian@ianbarton.co.uk"&gt;Ian Barton.&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2019 15:08:08 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Backpacking In Wales By Showell Styles</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2011-01-16-backpacking-in-wales-by-showell-styles/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Showell_Styles"&gt;Showell Styles&lt;/a&gt; (known to his friends as "Pip") was a prolific author
with over 160 published books. I think that I first became aware of
his mountaineering writing when I used to read "Climber and Rambler",
where he published several articles. He also contributed to Ken
Wilson's "Classic Rock" writing about three climbs on the East Face of
Tryfan.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Backpacking in Wales&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/backpacking_in_wales.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Backpacking in Wales"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/backpacking_in_wales.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
My father was an avid reader of seafaring books and one day I noticed
him reading a book by Showell Styles and that's how I found about his
fiction. Although I have my father's copies of many of his seafaring
fiction, I have never read any of his mountaineering books.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A few months ago I read a post on &lt;a href="http://www.outdoorsmagic.com/forum/forummessages/mps/dt/1/UTN/38309/V/1/SP/"&gt;Outdoors Magic&lt;/a&gt; which described
following one of Styles' routes described in his "Backpacking in
Wales" book the "Bay to Bay" walk. After reading the post I decided I
would also like to read "Backpacking in Wales". Although Styles books
have long been out of print, most of them are available from second
hand booksellers. A quick search showed up several copies, but for
some reason they were all priced between £20 and £35. This seemed a
little strange because almost all of Styles other books are available
for less than £10. Even stranger - if I visited the US sites of these
same booksellers the same book was available for $6! For a while I
considered trying to order the book via the US site. The books
themselves were all dispatched from Britain, but I decided that this
probably wouldn't work.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today I was in Shrewsbury and went into a second hand book shop to see
if they had any mountaineering books. In the section with books about
Wales I found a copy of "Backpacking in Wales" in excellent condition
for £4.Unable to believe my good fortune, I promptly bought it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There is a plate inside the book showing it originally belonged to DAG
Hampton Davies. The plate has a Welsh inscription "Duw Gwir a Gwiad".
The book itself is divided into three sections "Journeys for a
Fortnight", "Journeys for a Week" and "Journeys for a Weekend". Each
day of a walk is preceded by a detailed route description, followed by
Styles' own account of the day.  haven't read all the book yet, but it
has already given me several new ideas for walks and Styles'
descriptions of the Welsh landscape and his journeys through it are
always worth reading.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
"Backpacking in Wales" by Showell Styles was published by Robert Hale (London)
in 1977.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>review</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2011-01-16-backpacking-in-wales-by-showell-styles/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Jan 2011 17:50:45 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>