<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ian's Blog. (Posts about cycling)</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/categories/cycling.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:ian@ianbarton.co.uk"&gt;Ian Barton.&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2019 12:44:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Decathlon Triban 500se</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2015-03-02-decathlon-triban-500SE/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Last year I bought a Giant Defy 2. However, I didn't want to ride it
through all the mud and salt in the winter months, so decided to buy a
cheap bike to use in winter. I did quite a bit of research and decided
to get a Decathlon Triban 500 SE. There is a more detailed review of the Triban 500SE
&lt;a href="http://road.cc/content/review/116333-btwin-triban-500-se-road-bike"&gt;road.cc&lt;/a&gt; .
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had to go into Decathlon with my daughter to buy some skiing
equipment and had  chance to look at the 500SE. It seemed to be a
decent bike for the price and I had read several positive reviews. I
ended up coming out of the store with one.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Decathlon Triban 500SE&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2015-03_triban/IMG_20150203_132015.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Decathlon Triban 500SE"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2015-03_triban/IMG_20150203_132015.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
After a few local rides of between 20 and 40 miles I was quite
impressed. The microshift gears (3x8) weren't as smooth a the Tiagra
on the Giant, but changes were positive with no missed gears. I have
got used to a compact gear set on the Giant, which I prefer to the
more traditional three front rings. However, there isn't anything
around here that's steep enough for me to need the small front ring,
so it wasn't really a problem. The saddle was a bit uncomfortable
after a couple of hours riding. However, it can't be that bad as I have a
better spare saddle at home and I haven't bothered changing it yet! The carbon
fork absorbs road vibrations nicely. The brakes do their job of
stopping you with minimum fuss, but I needed to pull a bit harder than
on the Giant.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I did change the tyres for Schwalbe Durano Plus folding tyres, as most
of my riding is along country lanes, where punctures from hedge
cuttings are common.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Having ridden it for a couple of months the freewheel packed up about
5 miles from home. I had to call out International Rescue and put the
bike in the boot of the car. Decathlon didn't have any freewheels in
stock, so gave me a complete new wheel. Definitely excellent customer
service. They showed me the broken freewheel which had rusted and the
bearings were badly worn on the drive side. I wash my bike after every
ride in the winter and am careful not to get detergent or GT85
anywhere near bearings.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Rear cassette after 1500 miles&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2015-03_triban/IMG_20150224_164314.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Rear cassette after 1500 miles"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2015-03_triban/IMG_20150224_164314.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
After 1500 miles the gears began to skip. Measuring the chain it didn't appear
unduly worn. However, the teeth on the cassette looked just like
sharks teeth! My LBS replaced the cassette and chain, plus the cables.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So what's the final verdict. Overall I am happy with the Triban. I
enjoy riding it and I don't worry too much it getting plastered in
muck and grit. For the price it's a good buy, but don't expect the
drive chain to be as durable as a more expensive bike.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cycling</category><category>review</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2015-03-02-decathlon-triban-500SE/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2015 17:59:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>C2c Prologue</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-08-24-C2C-Prologue/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
There are a number of Coast to Coast cycle rides in the UK. This
series of posts is about the ride that starts at either Workington or
Whitehaven and finishes at Tynemouth or Sunderland. Depending on the
route you choose the ride is around 140 miles long with approximately
15,000 ft (altitude calculated from my GPS tracks) of ascent. We had
decided to do the ride over three days.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There were five of us planning to do the ride: my son with two of his
friends and one of my brothers in law. My brother in law could only
join us for the last two days. Also I wanted to let my son ride in a
group with his friends, without having his ancient Dad tagging
along. This meant that I  was effectively riding solo,  since I
do almost all my cycling alone this suited me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had done the Way of the Roses last year on my hybrid bike. I had
carried a fair bit of gear in panniers. For the C2C I decided to use
my road bike and carry a minimal amount of gear in a rucksack. Most
cyclists don't like carrying a rucksack, but since I do a lot of
walking and climbing, I find I prefer to carry things in a rucksack
rather than in panniers. As I was using my road bike, I made a couple
of modifications to the "Official Route". On the descent from
Whinatter I followed the road, rather than the track through the
forest. Leaving Keswick I cycled past Castlerigg Stone circles before
rejoining the C2C at Threlkeld, thus avoiding the railway track. On
day three I avoided cycling along the Waskerley Way, taking the B road
that runs parallel to it. However, my son, who was also on his road
bike cycled, along the Waskerley Way and said it was fine.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Depending on the route you take the C2C is around 140 miles long with
approximately 16,600ft (5,320 metres) of ascent. Most people do the
route over several days. We had decided to do it in three days. Day
one was Whitehaven to Keswick. We chose Keswick as the destination
because my son and his friends were staying at one of his friend's
grandmother's house. This turned out to be a good choice as the ride
wasn't too hard, so was a nice introduction to the route.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Day two was Keswick to Allenheads. I chose the destination on the
basis that it Allenheads was supposed to be the end of the big hills,
so day three would be a nice easy ride. This turned out to be quite a
short day and it turned out that there were two more big hills beyond
Allenheads!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Day three was Allenheads to Tynemouth/Sunderland. My son and his
friends had chosen to finish at Sunderland where one of his friends
parents was going to pick them up an drive them home. My brother in
law and I planned to finish at Tynemouth. However, I had to get back
to Whitehaven and then drive four hours to get home, as we were going
on holiday the next day. My brother in law had done the route
previously and knew that we couldn't take cycles on the metro, so
would have to cycle the ten miles from Tynemouth back to Newcastle
station. I wasn't that bothered about going all the way to the coast,
so we finished at Newcastle station.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
See my rant about rail transport arrangements for the C2C.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf7e78df" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgf7e78df"&gt;Accomodation.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgf7e78df"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd5c4530" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgd5c4530"&gt;Day 0 (Pre-ride).&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgd5c4530"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We drove up the day before our first stage. My son and his friends
stayed at the The Waverley Hotel hotel in Whitehaven, whilst I stayed
at &lt;a href="http://www.chestnuts-whitehaven.com"&gt;Chestnuts&lt;/a&gt; about three miles outside Whitehaven. If you like animals
I can thoroughly recommend Chestnuts. The owners are very helpful and
accommodating. The B&amp;amp;B is comfortable and the breakfasts good and they
will serve you an early breakfast if you want an early start. The
owners run a small animal sanctuary, in addition to having several
pets of their own. There are dogs, cats, chinchillas, a parrot and
some owls.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc179098" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgc179098"&gt;Day 1 - Keswick.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgc179098"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I stayed in the Travelodge on the A66, just outside Keswick. This can
be reached by following a cycle path from the roundabout complex over
the M6. This Travelodge has recently been renovated and the rooms seem
better than the average Travelodge. Don't rely on the Little Chef
opening at 7:00am, as it claims. There is a notice stuck to the door
saying it opens at 8:00am. However, Morrisons serve good and cheap breakfasts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org339606b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org339606b"&gt;Day 2 - Allenheads.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org339606b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I stayed at &lt;a href="http://www.allenheadsc2c.com"&gt;Newhouses&lt;/a&gt; which is a very comfortable B&amp;amp;B just on the edge
of the village, up a steep stone track. This was very comfortable with
a residents lounge and an excellent breakfast. My son and his friends
stayed at the ???, which they said was fine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org90b6a5d" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org90b6a5d"&gt;Useful Books and Web Sites.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org90b6a5d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I found the &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/C2C-Cycle-Route-Cicerone-Guides-ebook/dp/B00A2MKYO8/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1411372919&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=c2c+cicerone"&gt;Cicerone&lt;/a&gt; guide a great source of information before and
during the ride. I decided to buy the Kindle version. For me the only
disadvantage of the Kindle version was that the maps aren't zoomable,
so are basically unreadable on a small screen. However since I had a
paper map this didn't matter to me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;a href="http://www.c2c-guide.co.uk/"&gt;C2C&lt;/a&gt; web site is the official resource for the ride and contains
lots of information.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org1081b9d" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org1081b9d"&gt;Map.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org1081b9d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Although the route is very well signposted, carrying a map is highly
recommended. I used the &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1901389650/ref=pd_lpo_sbs_dp_ss_1?pf_rd_p=479289247&amp;amp;pf_rd_s=lpo-top-stripe&amp;amp;pf_rd_t=201&amp;amp;pf_rd_i=1852846496&amp;amp;pf_rd_m=A3P5ROKL5A1OLE&amp;amp;pf_rd_r=1YC5Z8C9KDRGP64NK2R6"&gt;Sustrans&lt;/a&gt; official map. The map shows both on
road and off road alternatives. It was well worth buying. However,
there are a couple of minor niggles:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no grid lines, which makes it hard to cross reference your
position using a GPS or OS map.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In order to fit all the ride onto one map, it only shows a narrow
strip. Thus it's hard to see places of interest, or route
alternatives without referring to another map.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Despite these minor niggles, I would recommend that you buy the map.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org75ebcda" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org75ebcda"&gt;Ride Statistics.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org75ebcda"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Times are taken from my GPS logs. The exclude major stops at
cafes. However, they do include minor stops such as 30min or so  to
fix a puncture outside Keswick. Altitudes and distances are taken
directly from the GPS log.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The initial section of day two doesn't include the steep climb from
the centre of Penrith up to Beacon Edge because I forgot to start the
GPS and I wasn't about to drop back down the hill and cycle up it again!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In retrospect if I did the ride again, I would go further on the
second day, or do the whole thing in two days. My brother in law had
previously done the ride in two days, going from Whitehaven to
Allenheads in one day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgef95aa4" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgef95aa4"&gt;Day One.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgef95aa4"&gt;
&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="hsides"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Whitehaven to Penrith&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Distance miles/km&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Ascent ft/metres&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Total Time&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;3 hrs 10 min (includes fix puncture) to Keswick&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;54.6 (87.4)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;5961 (1834)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;5:40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;2 hrs 30 min to Penrith&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org28f0953" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org28f0953"&gt;Day Two.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org28f0953"&gt;
&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="hsides"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Penrith to Allenheads&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Distance miles/km&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Ascent ft/metres&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Time&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Penrith to Hartside Cross (cafe) 1hr 53 min&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;33.6 (53.8)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;5177 (1593)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;3:57&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Hartside to Allenheads 2hr 4min&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org953401b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org953401b"&gt;Day Three.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org953401b"&gt;
&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="hsides"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Allenheads to Newcastle&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Distance miles/km&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Ascent ft/metres&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Time&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;4hrs 33mins&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;44.3 (70.9)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;3569 (1098)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;4:33&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc58b29d" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgc58b29d"&gt;Train Rant!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgc58b29d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had hope to do the ride without needing to use the car. Getting from
Crewe to Whitehaven with a bike didn't seem too problematic, although
bikes have to be pre-booked and the number of spaces aren't known
until you try to make your booking. However, getting back from
Tynemouth to Whitehaven was a different matter. I discovered from my
brother in law, who had done the ride before, that you can't take
cycles on the metro from Tynemouth back into the centre of Newcastle.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once back in Newcastle, you have to catch a train to Carlisle, then
another one to Whitehaven. At present both services are run by
Northern Rail. Their web site promises:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Northern is strongly committed to promoting cycling as a sustainable
and healthy means of transport that complements our train service. Our
vision is to 'connect people to opportunities by the most sustainable
means' and cycling has an important role to play. We want to do more
to make this an attractive option so we are working with local
authorities and the cycling community to see where we can make our
stations more cycle-friendly.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Bikes are carried free of charge at any time and you don't need to make reservations.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The cycle space on trains is clearly marked, both internally and
externally. Space is allocated on a first come, first served basis.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We can only carry a maximum of two bikes per train but conductors have
responsibility for the safety of their train and have the right to
refuse entry if the train is busy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Note that bikes can't be pre-booked and there are only two spaces per
train. So after a three day ride, you don't know if you can actually
get your bike on a train. The C2C is one of the most popular long
distance cycle routes in England, with hundreds of people completing
it each year. The provision of two bike spaces per train is derisory!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In practice the train from Newcastle to Carlisle had more spaces
(probably around 6). However, the Carlisle to Whitehaven service did
only have two spaces. Luckily the conductor was happy to let extra
bikes onto the train. We could just as easily have been unlucky and
had to wait for possibly days for a space. It's not as though
installing extra spaces is expensive, or complicated. Also it has
minimal impact on the total number of passengers that can be carried.
So Northern Rail how about living up to your grand "Mission Statement"
and actually provide a proper cycle carriage service.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cycling</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-08-24-C2C-Prologue/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2014 17:58:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>C2c Day Two</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-08-23-C2C-Day-Two/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Le Grand Depart&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140813_090832.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Le Grand Depart"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140813_090832.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
We had originally planned this section to complete the major climbs of
the middle section in one day. It turned out to be a very short day,
about three and a half hours (excluding tops). In retrospect it would have been better
to continue beyond Allenheads, but as we had pre-booked accomodation
this wasn't possible. With a bit more planning we could have probably
completed the route in two days, although for me, this would have been
pushing it a bit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We had arranged to meet my son and his friends at the place they were
staying in Penrith about 8:30am. We had planned to have breakfast at
the Little Chef, but although the pillar on the outside said it would
open at 7:00am, it turned out that it wouldn't in fact open until
8:00am. Somewhat fed up, I decided to cycle down into Penrith and have
breakfast at Morrisons. After breakfast, I cycled up the steep hill to
the house where my son was staying. The house was actually on the C2C,
which made initial route finding straightforward.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My son and his friends raced off in front while my brother in law and
myself followed at a more sedate pace. Once again the weather looked
decidedly dodgy, with cloud obscuring the moors in front of us. We
passed through Langwathby . There followed several sections of up and
down, but nothing too steep. We could see cars climbing the A686, high
up on the moors, in the distance. The tops were covered in cloud, so
we couldn't see that cafe.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Looking back from Hartside cafe&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140813_105959.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Looking back from Hartside cafe"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140813_105959.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
From the description I had expected the hill up to Hartside to be
challenging. However, it turned out to be much easier than many of the
other lesser hills. It's long, but apart from a very short section,
where the route joins the main A686, it's not particularly steep. I
managed to maintain a respectable pace and only stopped to take
photos. I arrived at the cafe just as the cloud lifted. I couldn't
have timed it better. The cafe wasn't too busy and a couple of cups of
tea with an apricot slice were very welcome.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The descent from the cafe was very pleasant. Although it's on an A
road, there was very little traffic. Not having seen any traffic for
the last three miles, as soon as I wanted to turn right at Leadgate a
veritable convoy suddenly appeared behind me. The ride down into
Garigill was pleasant. However, the initial section out of there was a
shocker. After overcoming the very steep start, the hill goes
on, and on, and on. However, the subsequent sections aren't too steep and there
are fine views all around. We stopped for a drink and some food at the
top of the hill before beginning the descent towards Nenthead. Just
before arriving at Nenthead there is a very steep descent. This
culminates in a couple of very sharp bends and the road is very
potholed. There are several signs warning you to slow down. Take note!
Going too fast will result in a painful crash.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Crossing into Northumberland&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140813_130528.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Crossing into Northumberland"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/IMG_20140813_130528.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
My wife was waiting at Nenthead and we stopped for a chat and some
more to drink.  After an initial steep climb out of the village we
turned off along the B road to climb up to the top of Black Hill, the
highest point of the C2C. There follows a short descent before another
small hill. After that it's a great downhill ride all the way to
Allenheads.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;View from above Nenthead&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140813_130640.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="View from above Nenthead"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140813_130640.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
The village of Allenheads is quite stretched out and the pub and our
accommodation were at the far end. My son and his friends stayed in
the pub,  ee stayed at &lt;a href="http://www.allenheadsc2c.com"&gt;Newhouses&lt;/a&gt;, which was a
short way out of the village up a track. The proprietor seemed very
confused about exactly who she had booked in, despite email
confirmations. However, we sorted it out eventually. The accommodation
was superb. The rooms were large and comfortable. Downstairs there was
a separate residents lounge and kitchen.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After a short rest, we wandered down into the village to join the
others at the pub. We had an enjoyable meal and a few drinks before
wandering back up the road to our beds.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cycling</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-08-23-C2C-Day-Two/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2014 17:58:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>C2c Day Three</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-08-23-C2C-Day-Three/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sculpture on the outskirts of Consett&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140814_11312.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Sculpture on the outskirts of Consett"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140814_11312.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
When I got up in the morning, I felt slightly sick and couldn't eat
much of the excellent breakfast. Luckily I recovered after a couple of
hours on the bike, but was a bit worried about how the day might go.
I wanted to get to Newcastle as early as possible, so I would be able
to get back to Whitehaven in time to drive home. I was also worried
about not being able to get my bike on the train.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Almost as soon as I left the village there was a steep hill. This lead
through a series of tight bends and was hemmed in by forestry. Just
what you don't need first thing when not feeling too well! However, I
made it to the top, where a van was disgorging the beaters for the
days grouse shooting. The following downhill section to Rookhope was
the most enjoyable descent of the whole trip. It's just the right
gradient to coast, with the occasional boost from the pedals.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In Rookhope I ignored the off road section and continued on along the
road to Stanhope. The climb out of Stanhope was without question the
toughest of the whole C2C.  Overall the hill wasn't too bad, but there
are two sections of 1 in 3 or 1 in 4 near the start. I managed the
first section, but gave up and walked on the second one. Eventually
the road reaches the start of the Waskerley Way. I wasn't sure about
doing this on a road bike, although my son took this route and said it
was fine. I needed to do even more climbing before I reached a small B
road that descended parallel to the Waskerley Way. This was a great
descent, most of it just coasting along. At the end there was a bit of
ascent to rejoin the Waskerley Way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the outskirts on Consett I stopped for a breather and the others
caught me up. We cycled past the old smelt wagon at Widgetts Junction
and missed out turn off to Newcastle. Luckily a local cyclist helped
us out with directions and we were soon back on the right route. Most
of the rest of the route follows an old railway with a good surface. I
just wanted to get to the end, so just put my head down and pushed
on. Finally I emerged next to the river and got a bit confused when I
seemed to be cycling the wrong way. However, it turned out OK as I
needed to reach the A695 road bridge to cross the river. From here the
C2C shares the route with the Hadrians Way cycle path.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I could seen some rain blowing up the river towards me and about two
miles from the end I was engulfed in a downpour. There was no point in
stopping to get out waterproofs, as I was soaked in a few seconds. I
ploughed on, stopping only to ask someone in a bus shelter how to get
to the station. His directions were spot on, but finding the entrance
was problematic. I met up with my brother in law, who was having the
same problem! Eventually, we got into the station where a very helpful
member of staff told us that there was a train to Carlisle leaving in
about 10 minutes. We raced onto the platform, where we discovered that
this train had space for six bikes and all the slots were empty, so we
had at least got our bikes onto this train OK.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once I sat down I started to feel very cold. I had no spare clothes,
so just dripped and shivered all the way to Carlisle. There was a
train to Whitehaven ready to depart. This train does only have two
bike spaces, but the guard was fine about me just sitting and holding
onto my bike. Finally I was back in Whitehaven in the early
afternoon. I went to Tescos for a hot drink and some food before
cycling back to &lt;a href="http://www.chestnuts-whitehaven.com"&gt;Chestnuts&lt;/a&gt; to pick up the car. I had a brief chat with
the owners before setting off back home. Unfortunately, junction 16 on
the M6 was closed at night for repairs. I could have come off at an
earlier junction, but there were no signs before junction 16
indicating that it was closed! This added an unnecessary extra 30
miles to my journey.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I spite of the drenching and extra unnecessary 30 miles driving home,
I had enjoyed the last day. I would like to do the route again, but
next time I'll try and do in two days.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cycling</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-08-23-C2C-Day-Three/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2014 17:58:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>C2c Day One</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-08-23-C2C-Day-One/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I left &lt;a href="http://www.chestnuts-whitehaven.com"&gt;Chestnuts&lt;/a&gt; around 8:30am and cycled down into Whitehaven. I
cycled down to the harbour, but didn't bother going all the way along
to the C2C sign. The initial section out of Whitehaven is fairly grim. The
cycling is easy, but the route goes through several housing estates
and the path is littered with large collection of dog turds and broken
glass. Luckily this section isn't too long and I was soon following
the old railway line. The off road sections are almost all on tarmac
so fine on a road bike. There was a short section of rather bumpy
track just before Rowrah which would be unpleasant on a road bike if
it was very wet.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bassenthwaite from near Cockermouth&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140812_104902.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Bassenthwaite from near Cockermouth"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140812_104902.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
The weather, which had been fine for weeks looked decidedly dodgy. The
day before the tail end of a hurricane had passed through. The fells in
front were covered in cloud and there was a very strong wind. Luckily
the wind was blowing from the west, so was in fact a big help!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There is a stiff climb out of Kirkland, but the extra altitude gives
you great views over the surrounding countryside. There is a pleasant
downhill section to Lamplugh, with a stiff climb at the end. I was
headed towards Loweswater, but the view of the lake is obscured by
Burnbank. After a downhill section to Waterend I could finally see the
lake.  The road follows Loweswater, with some minor ups and downs
until you reach the village. I headed towards Brackenthwaite along a
narrow road with plenty of ups and downs. At the village of Low Lorton
there is a very steep section. Thankfully it's short and it deposits
you at the bottom of the Whinlatter Pass.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Saddleback Cafe Keswick&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140812_130719.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Saddleback Cafe Keswick"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140812_130719.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
The climb up Whinlatter isn't to bad and there is a Visitor Centre at
the top, which I didn't bother visiting. I stopped i one of the car
parks to chew through an oat bar and have a drink. I realized how cold
and windy it was, as in about five minutes I went from an overheated
sweaty lump to a shivering lump! I can't really see the point of
following the forestry track, which looks steep and loose. The road is
fairly quiet. It is very steep in places, so you need to keep a check
on your speed and make sure that you can make it round the next bend,
without colliding with an oncoming car. At the bottom I crossed a
small suspension bridge over the Derwent. A short section along
a railway track emerged next to the A66. There is a good cycle track
alongside the road. It was on this track that I experienced the only
puncture of the trip. There was an explosive bang and the rear tyre
went flat instantly. I couldn't find anything that might have caused
this to happen and there was nothing stuck in the tyre. I had soon
fitted a new tube and continued the short distance into Keswick.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Keswick reminded me why I don't visit the Lakes anymore. It took about
five minutes before there was a break in the traffic, so I could cross
the road. The town itself was absolutely ram packed full of people
and almost every shop was some sort of outdoors emporium, with almost
no real shops.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;A proper doorstep sandwich&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140812_124053.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="A proper doorstep sandwich"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140812_124053.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
I still had one spare tube, but I bought another at
&lt;a href="http://www.keswickbikes.co.uk"&gt;KeswickBikes&lt;/a&gt;. While I was there I bought a Cateye rear light, as my
son had commandeered mine for his bike. I wasn't expecting to be
riding in the dark, but having some sort of highly visible light in
case of heavy rain, or poor visibility is always a good idea. I
settled into the Saddleback cafe, which is next to Keswick Bikes. I
had a "proper" cheese and pickle doorstep wedge sandwich. While I was
eating it, the heavens opened and rain poured down. Fortunately, by
the time I had finished lunch the rain had blown over.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I made my way slowly through the centre of Keswick, which given the
amount of traffic was probably the most dangerous part of the
journey. I arrived at the bottom of the steep series of climbs up to
Castle Rigg Stone Circle. On one section I was going so slowly that I
was overtaken by a runner. Oh the shame and embarrassment! Finally I
made it to the stone circle, where I stopped for a rest. A few years
ago we had visited them with the children on a ride that went out of
Keswick along the old railway track and returned past the stone
circle.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I made a mistake shortly after the stone circle and turned left too
soon. This brought me out on the A66, with no option of avoiding
cycling along it. Fortunately I didn't have to cycle back too far to
get on the right route, which brought me out near Threlkeld. Past
Scales the road turns north on a narrow lane leading to
Mungrisdale. The lane had plenty of gates, so  every time I got into a
nice rhythm I had to get off to open and close a gate. Although
Mungrisdale is a pleasant enough place, it seems as if the C2C
deliberately chooses to meander about when a more direct route is
possible. I kept seeing signs on the A66 telling me that Penrith was
10 miles away, but I ended up cycling nearer 20! After another long
meander through Greystoke (home of Tarzan), it was finally time to
drop down into Penrith.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I made straight for Morrisons, where I had a large Bakewell tart and a
pot of tea. I received a text from my son, who is a lot fitter than me
and had arrived some time before. I was staying in the Travelodge on
the A66, where my wife was going to join me.  I was a bit worried how
I was going to get there, as I really didn't fancy cycling down the
A66. Luckily, there is a cycle path that leads alongside the A66
directly to the Travelodge.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Castlerigg stone circle&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140812_132829.jpg" class="rounded
float-left" alt="Castlerigg stone circle"&gt;&lt;img src="https://ianbarton.co.uk/galleries/2014-08-C2C/IMG_20140812_132829.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;




&lt;p&gt;
The Travelodge had recently been refurbished and had decent size
rooms, pleasantly decorated. Travelodges can be cheap to stay in, but
recently seem to have been involved in a race to the bottom to cut facilities
and maintenance to the minimum to save costs. However, I would be
happy to stay in the Keswick one again! We had tea in the Little Chef
next door - I thought these were extinct.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was happy with my performance on day one. I hadn't found the ride
hard and wasn't particularly tired.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cycling</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-08-23-C2C-Day-One/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2014 17:58:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Wirral Way</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-02-23-The-Wirral-Way/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description></description><category>cycling</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2014-02-23-The-Wirral-Way/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2014 17:57:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tour Of Britain</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2013-09-22-Tour-of-Britain/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;!– PELICAN&lt;sub&gt;BEGIN&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/sub&gt; –&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Tour of Britain." href="/static/images/2013-09&lt;sub&gt;tour&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;of&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;britain&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7905.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Tour of Britain." title="Tour of Britain." src="/static/images/2013-09&lt;sub&gt;tour&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;of&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;britain&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7905.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a keen cyclist I was pleased to hear that stage four of the &lt;a href="http://tourofbritian.co.uk"&gt;Tour of
Britain&lt;/a&gt; was passing within a couple of miles of where I lived. I
decided that the best place to get a good view was outside the local
pub, where the race had to negotiate a "T" junction. The race was due
to pass the pub about 12:00pm, so I left home shortly after eleven on
the 20 minute ride, to give my self plenty of time to find a good
spot.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;!– PELICAN&lt;sub&gt;END&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/sub&gt; –&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even though we were in the depths of the Shropshire countryside there
was a good turn out of spectators, many of whom arrived by cycle. I
hadn't realized how much organization was involved in getting the
Peleton safely along the route. Police motorycle outriders started
arriving about 20 mins. before the riders. In all there must have been
around 20 motorbikes ahead of the peleton.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally the lead breakaway group, which was about two and a half
minutes ahead of the peleton arrived. I hadn't appreciated how fast
the riders would be cycling. Even going round the T junction they were
going so quickly that most of my photos were blurred. After the
peleton zoomed past, I resumed my ride, getting in a very modest 20
mile round trip back home.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cycling</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2013-09-22-Tour-of-Britain/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2013 17:56:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Connemara</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2012-12-27-Connemara/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
The West coast of Ireland is great for cycling. The coastal scenery
is spectacular and the roads are quiet. This circular route takes the
??? peninsula just south of Clifden. It's worth noting the wind
direction before starting out, as it can often be quite breezy and a
bit of advance planning will minimize the distance you are peddling
into the wind. This was to be a family ride.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We parked in a layby just outside Ballyconneely, but there are
numerous parking places all around the route. In fact you could
easily start from Clifden. We decided to cycle anti-clockwise, which
meant that on the day the first part of the ride was into the
wind. As is often the case in Ireland, the weather was fickle and
there were frequent sharp showers. We had planned to stop at one of
the beaches before we reached Roundstone, but decided to press
on. Shortly before Roundstone there is a bit of an ascent, followed
by a nice long descent to the beach at Gurteen Bay.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The girls were getting fed up of peddling into the wind and getting
soaked on a regular basis. We agreed that they would stop in
Roundstone and I would continue around the rest of the loop and fetch
the car. I set off only pausing in Roundstone to buy some
chocolate. The town is in idyllic spot next to the sea.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I thought that the section of the ride from Roundstone was the
highlight. After following the road along the coast you take a left
turn and climb up over the moors of Roundstone Bog. There are great
views of the Twelve Bens to the North. The ground either side of the
road is very boggy and there are hundreds of small pools. This section
of the ride is very exposed and wouldn't be a good place to be in
really bad weather. The wind was now behind me, which only increased
my enjoyment of this section of the ride.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Soon I reached the junction with the main road from Clifden. Shortly
after you rejoin the road, you can follow a track up to the left,
which takes you to the Alcock and Brown landing site. THey were the
first people to fly over the Atlantic and given the nature of the
terrain it's amazing that they weren't killed on landing. The track
takes you up to the site of the old Marconi radio station and a large
concrete obelisk commemorating the flight. The actual landing site is
about 500m from the obelisk. If you want to visit it, be prepared for
some bog trotting and wet feet.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I cycled back along the track to rejoin the main road and was soon
back at Ballyconneely. By the time I had driven over to Roundstone
the girls had set off and I caught up with them just as they turned
off to Roundstone Bog.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cycling</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2012-12-27-Connemara/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2012 17:55:11 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Circular Ride From Whitchurch</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2012-12-14-Circular-Ride-from-Whitchurch/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
The route is described starting from Whitchurch, but since it's
circular, you could start from anywhere. There is only one short
steep hill between Tittenley and Calverhall. Apart from Whitchurch,
which does have some cycle lanes, most of the route is on quiet
country lanes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
From Whitchurch turn up Claypit Street, which is just before the new
Sainsbury. Alternatively, you can follow Sustrans Route 45. The road
leads slowly uphill past a cemetary and the ??? camping farm. A
downhill section leads to a left hand bend, where you take the road
(Ossmere Lane) on the right. Shortly after crossing the railway you
will join Sustrans Route 45, which comes in from the right. If you
look in the hedge on the left hand side your will see ???? Mercian
statue.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the T junction turn right into Hollyhurst road. You will be able to
see and obelisk to your right, which is a war memorial in the grounds
of Combermere Abbey. Shortly before you go underneath he railway,
there is a style and a grassy area on the right, which provides a
convenient stopping place to eat and drink. Immediately after you go
under the railway bridge turn right and then a short distance further
on turn right again at a fork in the road. You are now on Sustrnas
route 70. This will lead you through Aston, past the corn mills, to the main Whitchurch -
Nantwich road. Cross this and head off along Shepenhall Lane. Ignore
all the turnings to the left and right. Just after you cross over a
brook Shepenhall Lane changes into Rookery Lane.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Cross over the main road to Audlem and follow Royals Green
Lane. After half a mile or so, you will come to a T junction opposite
the end of Wilkesley Wood. Turn left along Wilkesley Lane and cycle
through the hamlet of Wilkesley. After about a mile and a half, at
the end of a long red brick wall you will pass the two lodges which
were one of the entrances to the Shavington Estate. Carry on along
the road until it bends sharply to the left. At this point you need
to take the lane to the right, which leads past the large pool at
Tittenley, on your left hand side.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Shortly after passing the Tittenley pool there are another two lodges,
which mark what used to be another entrance to the Shavington
Estate. Turn up the lane to the right, which is the only real climb on
this route. It doesn't last very long and leads you to another T
junction. Turn right here (signposted Calverhall). After half a mile
of so you will pass the grand iron gates, which were the main entrance
to the Shavington Estate. Carry on until you reach the small village
of Calverhall. The Jack pub on the left is well worth a visit and
serves good food and beer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Turn right at the T junction and cycle into Ightfield. There is a
convenient brick bus shelter here, which is a good place to eat your
sandwiches if it's raining. Follow the bend round to the left. Just
on the right there is a large grassy playground, with a couple of
benches. This is a nice place to eat your sandwiches in good weather!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The road continues on into the two villages of Ash. It's a short easy
climb and there is a nice duck pond where you can linger. From Ash the
road descends to meet the Whitchurch bypass. Cross straight over the
roundabout and enter a small industrial estate. Carry straight on at
the apex of the sharp left hand bend which allows you to regain the
old main road into Whitchurch, via a short stretch of footpath. From
here it's only a short ride back to the town centre.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgef0909b" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgef0909b"&gt;Cafes and Pubs.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgef0909b"&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jones Coffee House, House Green End, Whitchurch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Juan Cafe, Watergate St, Whitchurch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dusty Miller (pub) Wrenbury Tel:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Jack, Calverhall Tel:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf4cb3bb" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgf4cb3bb"&gt;Parking.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgf4cb3bb"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Free parking in Whitchurch, Aston and Wrenbury. If you know the area
there are plenty of laybys on the route where you can park.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org45c8b54" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org45c8b54"&gt;Stats.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org45c8b54"&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distance: 34km&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ascent: 302m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cycling</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2012-12-14-Circular-Ride-from-Whitchurch/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2012 17:55:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Lake Vyrnwy</title><link>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2012-04-17-lake-vyrnwy/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Lake Vyrnwy is an ideal route for children. Although the road around
the lake is open to traffic, its winding nature and the presence of
many other cyclists keeps motorists speeds down. The total distance
around the lake is around 12 miles and the road is almost completely
flat.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are several parking places around the lake, and a cafe near the
dam.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org0d6c0f2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0d6c0f2"&gt;A More Challenging Ride.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0d6c0f2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For those wanting a harder ride there is an absolutely fantastic ride
to Bala. It's usual to start the ride from Bala. There is around 600m
of ascent and the total length of the ride is about 35 miles. From
Bala the ride gains the col at Bwlch-y-Groes, which has fine views
over the Arans. At 1800ft this is the highest pass in Wales. You can
let your legs recover on the descent to the lake and have a well
earned piece of cake in the cafe near the dam. The way back to Bala
takes the other road from the end of the lake up through Cwm Hirnant
before descending back to Bala.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cycling</category><guid>https://ianbarton.co.uk/posts/2012-04-17-lake-vyrnwy/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2012 17:53:45 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>