<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ian's Mountaineering Blog. (Posts about tripreport)</title><link>https://ianbarton.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://ianbarton.com/categories/tripreport.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:ian@ianbarton.co.uk"&gt;Ian Barton.&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2019 16:42:51 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Cwm Eigiau Backpack</title><link>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2014-09-11-cwm-eigiau-backpack/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org228bba4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org228bba4"&gt;Day One Llyn Eigiau to Carnedd Llewelyn .&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org228bba4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The summer weather looked set to continue for at least a few more
days, so I decided to have another go at the walk that I had done in
July. On the last trip I had forgotten my stove, so had to complete
the whole walk in a very long ten hour day. his time I was planning to
climb Pen Llithrigg yr Wrach and traverse the ridge over Pen yr Helgi
Du and Craig yr Ysfa to a camp site a couple of hundred feet below the
summit of Carnedd Llewelyn.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="A hazy Carnedd Llewelyn  from Pen Llithrig yr Wrach." href="/images/2014-09-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8813.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="A hazy Carnedd Llewelyn  from Pen Llithrig yr Wrach." title="A hazy Carnedd Llewelyn  from Pen Llithrig yr Wrach." src="/images/2014-09-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8813.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I didn't leave home until mid-morning. When I arrived at the start of
the road up into Cwm Eigiau there were signs at the bottom of the road
warning of long delays. Luckily I wasn't held up by what turned out to
be fairly minor repairs. It was midweek, so there were only about
three cars in the car park when I pulled in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Although it was hot, the heat had made the atmosphere hazy and some of
the summits were obscured by mist. I double checked all my gear before
setting off to make sure that I hadn't forgotten something important
like the stove. Feeling confident that I hadn't forgotten anything I
set off along the track towards the reservoir. After about half a mile
I realized that I hadn't turned the GPS on! I seldom use the GPS for
navigation, but like to keep a record of my track.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Mist over Tryfan and the Glyders." href="/images/2014-09-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8817.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Mist over Tryfan and the Glyders." title="Mist over Tryfan and the Glyders." src="/images/2014-09-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8817.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I filled my 2 litre and 1 litre Platypus water bottles from the
reservoir and also the Travel Tap. I wasn't sure if this would be
enough, but it turned out towards the just about the right amount, as
I had about 500ml spare in the morning for the walk back. There are
not really any water sources on top of the Carneddau, except for some
stagnant peaty pools. In the past I have used water from these and
filtered it through the Travel Tap. I don't normally bother filtering
the water from the reservoir.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
Plodding along the track I soon reached the old quarry workings at ???
and stopped for a rest. For the first time I had brought the GoPro
video camera with me, so I made a couple of short videos of the
view. The path beyond the quarry is vague, so I headed up diagonally
towards the ridge. Sweating in the heat, I finally found the path
along the crest of the ridge that leads up to the summit of Pen
Llithrig yr Wrach.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On my last trip I had started to get cramp on the pull up to Pen yr
Helgi Du and wanted to avoid it this time. I stopped for a rest, drank
quite a lot of water and ate a couple of flapjacks.  Moel Siabod was
only just visible through the haze and the tops of Tryfan and the
Glyders were covered in mist. While I was resting on the summit a man
appeared up the slope from Pen yr Helgi Du. While chatting to him we
heard a Chough calling. I said that had seen several Grouse lower
down. Apparently Grouse numbers have dropped considerably since the
1970's when the moors were managed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Craig yr Ysfa and Pen yr Helgi Du at sunset." href="/images/2014-09-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8818.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Craig yr Ysfa and Pen yr Helgi Du at sunset." title="Craig yr Ysfa and Pen yr Helgi Du at sunset." src="/images/2014-09-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8818.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I dropped down to the col between Pen Llithrig yr Wrach and Pen yr
Helgi Du. The slope up to the summit of Pen yr Helgi Du didn't seem
too bad this time and I didn't get cramp in my legs. I walked along
the summit ridge and began the descent of the ??? ridge. It was here
that I met the only other person I saw all day. I stopped to let him
pass as he climbed towards the summit. The scramble down is quite
steep, but fairly short. If you don't like exposure, make sure that
you keep to the left (facing out). I was soon down at Bwlch Eryl
Farchog and began the climb towards Craig yr Ysfa. The atmosphere was
beginning to clear and the views were improving as evening began to
draw in. The short scramble up the rocky step was awkward with a heavy
sack, but I was soon standing on the summit of Craig yr Ysfa. I had a
quick look over the top at the pinaccles near the top of Amphitheatre
Buttress. I have done this climb several times in the past and it's
one of the best long mountaineering routes in Wales. The climbing is
easy apart from the short crux section. If you can jam, climbing the
crack to the top of a short wall is easy. There is then a very exposed
step right onto a small ledge. Faling off here would involve a long
fall into the gulley below. However, you can drop a long sling over a
pinnacle, which protects the step round and the ground above is
easier. The final section of easy climbing over the pinaccles is a
delightfully exposed scramble. Maybe next time I'll climb up from
Ogwen, dump my sack on the top, descend to the bottom, the climb back
up to my sack and camp on Carnedd Llewelyn.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was now around 5:30, so I decided to camp on the
flat grassy shelf on the SE ridge of Carnedd Llewelyn that I had used
a couple of times in the past:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
[2011 photos]({filename}./2011-09-05-carneddeau-summit-camp.md)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
 The site is quite sheltered and there
are several piles of rock nearby, which are useful tables. It's quite
near to the main path up Carnedd Llewelyn, but far enough away that
you are not likely to be noticed by people passing by. It was now
shortly after 6:00pm and there was nobody else visible anywhere on the
Carneddau. The site is a bit tussocky, but I had soon found a nice
flat area to pitch the tent. I pitched it with the door facing East,
overlooking Cwm Eigiau so I could see the dawn from the tent door.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I soon had the stove going and boiled enough water to make a hot
chocolate and re-hydrate a Bewell Chilli. Despite sitting in a pot
cosy for 10 minutes, the rice in the chilli didn't seem to have
rehydrated properly. I boiled some more water, poured it into the
pouch and waited another 5 minutes. The rice still didn't seem to be
properly cooked, but I ate it anyway. I was tired so after taking a
few photos I got into my sleeping bag. After a short rest, I got out
of the tent to set up the GoPro. I wanted to take a series of still
photos of the dawn at intervals of 30 seconds and then turn these into
a video of the sunrise. I spent some time fiddling around with the
various GoPro brackets that I had brought with me and eventually
managed to rig up something that locked to my walking pole. There then
followed a short pantomime, while I tried to find a spot in the grass
where I could push the walking into. Finding somewhere that didn't
have a rock a few inches under the ground proved difficult. When I had
found a good spot I set the GoPro up facing over Cwm Eigiau and then
retired to bed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Carnedd Llewelyn campsite at sunset." href="/images/2014-09-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8836.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Carnedd Llewelyn campsite at sunset." title="Carnedd Llewelyn campsite at sunset." src="/images/2014-09-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8836.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The GoPro is in a weather proof case, so if it rained it didn't
matter. Keeping it inside the tent isn't a good idea, as it's warmer
inside the tent than outside, or at least it should be! Taking the
camera from a warm tent to a cold outside usually results on
condensation on the lens which spoils your photos.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org99ab39d" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org99ab39d"&gt;Day Two - Return Via Gledrffordd.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org99ab39d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The battery life of a GoPro in time lapse mode is around two hours. It
was quite cold at 3000 feet, so I expected the battery life to be
shorter. I set an alarm for 5:30am, so I could turn the GoPro on to
start taking the time lapse photos some time before the sun came over
the horizon . I woke up before the alarm went off and the Eastern sky
was already beginning to glow red. I scrambled out of the tent and set
the GoPro off. I made myself a hot drink while I watched the horizon
as it gradually got lighter and the sun finally appeared. Unlike the
previous day the atmosphere was crystal clear and the summits were
clear of mist. However, by about 7:00am mist had drifted over from the
west and all the views were obscured.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;iframe width="420" height="315"
src="//www.youtube.com/embed/Gsb9mcleTiQ" frameborder="0"
allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I packed away and began the trudge up towards the summit of Carnedd
Llewelyn. I could see patches of blue above me, but all the views were
obscured. From the summit, I set off along the ridge heading towards
Foel Grach. I began descending and was about to get the map out to
check my position, when I dropped below the mist. I could now see the
path that descends to Gledrffordd. I thought about continuing over to
Foel Grach and then descending the ridge that leads from the summit down to Gledrffordd,
but the mist was coming and going over the summit. I didn't want to
walk all the way up to the summit only to find the view obscured by the mist.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Tent at dawn. Mist rolling in." href="/images/2014-09-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8850.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Tent at dawn. Mist rolling in." title="Tent at dawn. Mist rolling in." src="/images/2014-09-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8850.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The descent was straightforward and this time I didn't make the
mistake of climbing onto the top of Craig Eigiau, but contoured along
below the ridge. As I joined the Landrover track I met what appeared
to be a school party who were being shown how to find where they were
on the map by their teacher.  Further along the track I passed a man
and what appeared to be his daughter heading up the track. When I
reached the car park there were only two or three other cars parked
there. Being able to walk midweek is definitely and advantage if you
want the hills to yourself.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>mountaineering</category><category>tripreport</category><guid>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2014-09-11-cwm-eigiau-backpack/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2014 17:58:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Crimpiau</title><link>https://ianbarton.com/posts/-crimpiau/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;!– PELICAN&lt;sub&gt;BEGIN&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/sub&gt; –&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Path up to col above Llyn Crafnant." href="/images/2014-07-crimpiau/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8597.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Path up to col above Llyn Crafnant." title="Path up to col above Llyn Crafnant." src="/images/2014-07-crimpiau/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8597.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Two of my three children were away, so Anne and I decided to take our
remaining daughter for a couple of days in North Wales. Neither of them like
camping, so we stayed in the bunk room at the &lt;a href="http://www.bryntyrchinn.co.uk/"&gt;Bryn Tyrch&lt;/a&gt; in Capel Curig.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We arrived late afternoon and since it looked as though it was going
to be a fine evening, so I decided to walk over Crimpiau. I did this walk
with my son three years ago the last time we stayed at the hotel.
However, I had forgotten to bring either my camera or phone, so wasn't
able to take any photographs. This time I made sure that I had both of
them with me!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;!– PELICAN&lt;sub&gt;END&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/sub&gt; –&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Llyn Crafnant from Crimpiau." href="/images/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8610.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Llyn Crafnant from Crimpiau." title="Llyn Crafnant from Crimpiau." src="/images/2014-07-crimpiau/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8610.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Anne and Hannah wanted to go to Joe Browns in Capel Curig. I walked up
with them and then crossed the style to start up the path towards Llyn
Crafnant.  The last time I had done the walk the weather had been quite drizzly,
but today there were large patches of blue sky and broken cloud. It
was about 4:30pm and we had booked dinner at the hotel for 7:00pm. I
couldn't remember how long the walk had taken last time, but thought I
would be able to get back for seven. In the event this was a bit
optimistic and it was about 7:20pm! As anyone who has walked with me
can testify, I have never really planned how long a walk takes. My
stock answer is always "It will take as long as it takes". I just have
an overall plan of  what I want to do. On multi-day walks I just
continue until I find somewhere nice to camp, I am too tired or it
goes dark.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Creigiau Gleision from Crimpiau." href="/images/2014-07-crimpiau/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8611.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Creigiau Gleision from Crimpiau." title="Creigiau Gleision from Crimpiau." src="/images/2014-07-crimpiau/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8611.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It seemed a long way to the col above Llyn Crafnant. It's not possible
to see the lake from the col, so I carried on to a high point on a
small spur that overlooked part of the lake. There were good views over
to Creigiau Gleision. The last time I had climbed it was about 30 years
ago in driving rain. I can remember it had lots of false tops and was
boggy and heathery. I keep meaning to go back and climb it in good
weather, but somehow have always been distracted by its nearby neighbours.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Tryfan and Bristly Ridge from Crimpiau." href="/images/2014-07-crimpiau/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8612.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Tryfan and Bristly Ridge from Crimpiau." title="Tryfan and Bristly Ridge from Crimpiau." src="/images/2014-07-crimpiau/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8612.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I returned to the col and began the climb up Crimpiau. It's not
possible to tell exactly where on the ridge the summit is from
below, so I just followed the most obvious path hoping it would get me
there. It seemed a long way before  a final short steep pull landed me
next to some rocks. These seemed to be the highest point on the ridge,
although unlike most other Snowdonia peaks there was no cairn.  From
the top there were views along the Ogwen valley, over Capel Curig to
Snowdon and to Cader Idris in the south. As is often the case the
views from the smaller peaks are often better than from the high ones.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Ogwen Valley from Crimpiau." href="/images/2014-07-crimpiau/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8616.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Ogwen Valley from Crimpiau." title="Ogwen Valley from Crimpiau." src="/images/2014-07-crimpiau/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8616.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I dropped down from the summit and followed the ridge all the way down
to the small Llyn Coren. It is normally very boggy here. I remember
going past it with John on my last visit and following a path that
kept to the rocks above the boggy part. Luckily for me, it was
dry today. I had a bit of trouble finding the path beyond the lake
that descends back to Capel, but found it eventually without having
to consult the map.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Llyn Coren and Moel Siabod." href="/images/2014-07-crimpiau/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8620.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Llyn Coren and Moel Siabod." title="Llyn Coren and Moel Siabod." src="/images/2014-07-crimpiau/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8620.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the bottom of the descent, I missed the short cut that goes
directly down to the Bryn Tyrch, which I had taken with John last
time and ended up back outside the cafe in Capel Curig. A final trot
down the road into the bar, where a drink was waiting for me and I was
only 20 minutes late.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="A couple of wild ponies wanted their photo taken!" href="/images/2014-07-crimpiau/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8633.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="A couple of wild ponies wanted their photo taken!" title="A couple of wild ponies wanted their photo taken!" src="/images/2014-07-crimpiau/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8633.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had been lucky with the weather. The next day it poured down all
day. Anne and Hannah went to visit &lt;a href="http://www.llechwedd-slate-caverns.co.uk/Zipworld_Page.php"&gt;Bounce Below&lt;/a&gt; in the Llechwedd Slate
mines at Ffestiniog. As someone who hates "attractions", theme parks
and queuing for anything I wandered around the old slate workings near
Tanygrisiau.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Llynnau Mymbyr and Snowdon." href="/images/2014-07-crimpiau/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8638.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Llynnau Mymbyr and Snowdon." title="Llynnau Mymbyr and Snowdon." src="/images/2014-07-crimpiau/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8638.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>mountaineering</category><category>tripreport</category><guid>https://ianbarton.com/posts/-crimpiau/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2014 17:57:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Glasgwm</title><link>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2014-07-08-Glasgwm/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
*
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;!– PELICAN&lt;sub&gt;BEGIN&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/sub&gt; –&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="The Arenigs from the col below Glasgwm." href="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8510.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="The Arenigs from the col below Glasgwm." title="The Arenigs from the col below Glasgwm." src="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8510.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was going to visit a relative in Swansea and thought I could combine
the journey with an overnighter on Glasgwm.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had forgotten what a long haul it is from home to Dinas
Mawddwy.  I got to the small car park at the end of Cwm Cywarch about
5:30pm. Although the car park was nowhere near full, there were more
cars than I had seen on my previous visits. Various people were
returning from their day out and getting ready to depart for home. The
weather forecast was for a clear night, so I wanted to try some
astrophotography from the summit. A couple of years ago I bought a
Yongnuo  &lt;a href="http://www.linearconcepts.com/photography/reviews/photo1"&gt;MC-36B&lt;/a&gt;  intervalometer for my Canon DSLR. I have used it at home to
create time lapse photos and take astro pictures. I have an Velbon
tripod that belonged to my father, which I intended to lug up to the summit. I
finished packing my rucksack and strapped the tripod to
the outside.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;!– PELICAN&lt;sub&gt;END&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/sub&gt; –&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Windfarm on ???" href="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8513.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="The Arenigs from the col below Glasgwm." title="Windfarm on ???" src="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8513.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
I set off along the track and ended up outside the Bryn Hafod hut. There were
a couple of people sitting outside and I asked if the track behind the
hut continued up to the col above. They didn't know and I don't remember
passing the hut on my previous visits, so I guessed I had missed the
start of the path. I continued along a feint path behind the hut for
some way until it became obvious that I was way off route. I returned
back to the track where the the style I should have climbed over was now obvious!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Aran
Fawddwy from Glasgwm." href="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8516.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Aran
Fawddwy from Glasgwm." title="Aran
Fawddwy from Glasgwm." src="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8516.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was very hot with hardly a cloud in the sky. Luckily after a few
hundred feet most of the steep section of the route was in shade. I
plodded up the path towards the col. Some way below it I came out of
the shade. The sun was now low in the sky and shining almost directly in
my face. Even wearing sun glasses it was difficult to see where I was
going. I finally emerged at the col below Glasgwm drenched with
sweat.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Summit cairn Glasgwm." href="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8529.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Summit cairn Glasgwm." title="Summit cairn Glasgwm." src="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8529.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The way to the summit was straightforward, albeit a bit of a slog. It
was just a matter of following the fence which leads to within a few
yards of the summit cairn. There were fine views to the West with very
little heat haze. I could see the summit of Arenig Fawr, where I had
been a couple of weeks ago, although Moel Llyfnant, where I had camped
was hidden from sight. A final steep rise bought the summit cairn into
view. Llyn Bach just below the summit was almost dry. I continued past
the summit and climbed the stile at the end of Llyn y Fign. The llyn
is in a magnificient position with good views in almost every
direction. Even better for summit campers there was no need to carry
up a heavy load of water. I made my way to the flat grassy area just
to the north of the lake, where I had camped previously. There was a
pleasant westerly breeze which soon evaporated all the sweat.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Cader at sunset." href="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8533.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Cader at sunset." title="Cader at sunset." src="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8533.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I soon had the tent pitched and there was still a couple of hours until
sunset at around 8:45pm, I made a cup of hot chocolate and had some
porridge and raisins. When I had finished eating,  I grabbed the camera and began walking around
the summit plateau. Looking towards Cader I could see it would be
possible to take
a high level route and continue over its summit to Dolgelleau. A
future backpack. Over to
the South West I could see the wind turbines on ???.  As the sun sank
towards the horizon a layer of cloud formed, so I didn't get the
spectacular sunset that I saw last time. The top of Aran
Fawddwy glowed pink as did the summit cairn of Glasgwm, as the sun
sank below the clouds.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Sunrise over Aran Fawddwy." href="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8553.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Sunrise over Aran Fawddwy." title="Sunrise over Aran Fawddwy." src="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8553.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At this time of year it takes a long time for it to get really dark
after the sun has set, so I got into my sleeping bag for a couple of
hours to wait for the stars to appear. I woke up about 12:30am to see
a clear sky outside. The stars of the plough were clearly visible over
the top of my tent. I put the camera on the tripod and started taking
some photographs. However, my attempt was thwarted by condensation
forming on the lens. Not even leaving the camera for outside some time
to adjust to the temperature outside the tent made any
difference. Eventually I called it a night and went back to my
sleeping bag. I woke again at 5:30am and made breakfast - porridge
again! I got out of the tent and began to take photographs. However,
soon a layer of early morning cloud obscured the summit. I packed up
and began the descent back to the car. I dropped out of the mist some
way above the col, but most of the surrounding summits were misted
out. I had badly bruised my left big toe on my Carneddau trip a few
weeks ago, so the descent was quite slow. Although th toe had stopped
hurting, the nail had turned black and I didn't want to aggravate the
injury.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt; HEAD
&lt;code&gt;=====&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back at the car park a couple of cars had arrived and people were
departing for their walk. I threw my rucksack into the back of the
truck and got ready to resume my journey to Swansea.  I drove back
along the Cwm following the farmer with his sheep trailer. The road is
very narrow with few passing places, so it was good to have an
oncoming traffic detector in front of me!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="The Arenigs from the col below Glasgwm." href="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8510.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="The Arenigs from the col below Glasgwm." title="The Arenigs from the col below Glasgwm." src="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8510.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Windfarm on ???" href="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8513.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="The Arenigs from the col below Glasgwm." title="Windfarm on ???" src="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8513.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Aran
Fawddwy from Glasgwm." href="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8516.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Aran
Fawddwy from Glasgwm." title="Aran
Fawddwy from Glasgwm." src="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8516.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Summit cairn Glasgwm." href="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8529.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Summit cairn Glasgwm." title="Summit cairn Glasgwm." src="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8529.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Cader at sunset." href="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8533.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Cader at sunset." title="Cader at sunset." src="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8533.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Sunrise over Aran Fawddwy." href="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8553.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Sunrise over Aran Fawddwy." title="Sunrise over Aran Fawddwy." src="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8553.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; 60466b1fcd87fc4b16d55cf9a9958d51c4c8f779
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Cwm Cowarch." href="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8566.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Cwm Cowarch." title="Cwm Cowarch." src="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8566.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I drove back along the Cwm following the farmer with his sheep
trailer. The road is very narrow with few passing places, so it was
good to have an oncoming traffic detector in front of me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Craig Cowarch." href="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8570.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Craig Cowarch." title="Craig Cowarch." src="/images/2014-07-glasgwm/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8570.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back at the car park a couple of cars had arrived and people were
departing for their walk. I threw my rucksack into the back of the
truck and got ready to resume my journey to Swansea.  I drove back
along the Cwm following the farmer with his sheep trailer. The road is
very narrow with few passing places, so it was good to have an
oncoming traffic detector in front of me!
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>mountaineering</category><category>tripreport</category><guid>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2014-07-08-Glasgwm/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2014 17:57:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Arenigs</title><link>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2014-06-28-arenigs/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;!– PELICAN&lt;sub&gt;BEGIN&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/sub&gt; –&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Summit cairn and memorial Arenig Fawr." href="/images/2014-07-arenigs/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8460.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Summit cairn and memorial Arenig Fawr." title="Summit cairn and memorial Arenig Fawr." src="/images/2014-07-arenigs/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8460.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I have done this backpack a couple of times before. However, I had no
hesitation in repeating it. The Arenigs are relatively unfrequented
and have panoramic views over most of the mountains of North
Wales. The summit of Moel Llyfnant seems to be rarely visited, as there
are only vague signs of tracks leading up to the top.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;!– PELICAN&lt;sub&gt;END&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/sub&gt; –&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After a long period of settled good weather the Mountain Weather Information
Service was predicting an area of low pressure over Wales on Saturday
with a great deal of uncertainty about conditions. The summits were
going to be misted out early on and there was a possibility of heavy
showers. However, the forecast for Sunday was much better.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Moel Llyfnant appears from the mist." href="/images/2014-07-arenigs/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8466.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Moel Llyfnant appears from the mist." title="Moel Llyfnant appears from the mist." src="/images/2014-07-arenigs/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8466.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Driving along the A55,  I could see see clouds over the Carneddau, but it wasn't
raining. I stopped at Y Caban in Deniolen for a cup of tea and lemon
drizzle cake. It took the woman behindthe counter about five munutes
to ask me what I wanted to order, as she was looking at photos on here
phone, even though I was only standing a couple of feet away from
her. I ended up buying a slice of Bakewell to take my bill over £5, so
I could avoid a surcharge for paying by debit card.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I drove thought the Llanberis Pass, only the tops of the peaks
were covered by cloud. Continuing through Beddgelert I could see that
the summit of Cnicht was clear.  However, as I got close to Ffestiniog, I could see the
Moelwyns submerged in cloud and this part of Wales seemed to be having
much worse weather than further west. However, I decided to keep going
as MWIS had promised an improvement in the weather as the day went on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Small pools on the South ridge of Arenig Fawr." href="/images/2014-07-arenigs/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8471.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Small pools on the South ridge of Arenig Fawr." title="Small pools on the South ridge of Arenig Fawr." src="/images/2014-07-arenigs/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8471.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was after 12:30pm when I arrived in the car park opposite the
quarry at Clogwyn Maen Glogog. I could see the summit of Arenig Fach,
but mist was drifting around the top of Arenig Fawr. The quarry was
full of large concrete road sections. The electricity company were
rewiring the overhead pylons that run through the valley and using the
car park as an equipment dump. I sorted out my gear and set off on the
longish walk along the road towards the track leading up to Llyn
Arenig Fawr. Leaving the car opposite the quarry would greatly reduce
the road walking on the second day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="The descent to the col below Moel Llyfnant." href="/images/2014-07-arenigs/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8476.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="The descent to the col below Moel Llyfnant." title="The descent to the col below Moel Llyfnant." src="/images/2014-07-arenigs/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8476.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I reached the start of the track there was a large red sign at
the bottom saying it was closed. However, there was no work going on,
so I decided to ignore the sign. A short way up the track I could see
why it has been closed. The cables between the pylons ran right over
the track, which would be a major hazard for anyone underneath when
they were working on the pylons. Since it was Saturday there was no work going
on, although all around the valley I could see where they had laid the temporary
road surfaces under the pylons.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Cader Idris at dawn." href="/images/2014-07-arenigs/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8486.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Cader Idris at dawn." title="Cader Idris at dawn." src="/images/2014-07-arenigs/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8486.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I reached the bothy I took off my rucksack and had a look round
inside. It was clean and tidy. Written on an old biscuit tin lid was
the email address (arenigtony@gmail.com) of one of the people who
helps to maintain the bothy. I sat on one of the benches outside and
ate the huge slice of Bakewell that I had bought from Y Caban. After
lunch I walked the short distance up to the reservoir to fill my
Travel Tap.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The mist was partially covering the crags at the far end of the lake
as I began to make my way up the path. At the top of the first steep
section I met a man descending who told me that the summit was misted
out and there was a cold breeze. Last time I had climbed directly up
on the North ridge to get better views. However, this time there wasn't any
point, as I wouldn't be able to see anything. I just followed the main path
that countours along the slope below the ridge before a final slog up to the summit.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Mist filled valleys at dawn." href="/images/2014-07-arenigs/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8489.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Mist filled valleys at dawn." title="Mist filled valleys at dawn." src="/images/2014-07-arenigs/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8489.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The mist cleared a few times, but had descended again just before I
reached the summit. Just below the summit shelter I met a man and a
woman descending. Not surprisingly there wasn't anybody else on the
summit. The mist again cleared briefly but after a few seconds the
summit was covered again. After a short rest, I took a compass bearing
to make sure that I would be descending along the South ridge. Once
I had begun to descend below the south summit I dropped out of the
cloud. I could just about make out Moel Llyfnant on the other side of
the valley as layers of cloud drifted past, but the lakes at the end of the south ridge were clearly visible
below me. I made my way down the grass slope, using the fence as a
hand rail and along to the second
pool. I dropped my rucksack a short distance away from the pool and took my Platypus
bottles over to the pool. I had a bit of trouble finding a place on
the bank where I could reach into the pool without disturbing the peat
on the bottom. On my first visit, I had collected water from a small
stream at the start of the descent to the col below Moel
Llyfnant. However, last time I came this way the stream was dry and I suspected
it might be dry today. In the event I was proved right.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Tent on Moel Llyfnant." href="/images/2014-07-arenigs/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8497.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Tent on Moel Llyfnant." title="Tent on Moel Llyfnant." src="/images/2014-07-arenigs/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8497.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I used the pile of stones placed next to the wire fence that marks the
start of the descent to the col below Moel Llyfnant. There is an
indistinct path that leads down to the track at the col, whcih I
followed. The section at the bottom is often very wet, but after the
recent dry spell my feet only got slightly damp as I tussock
jumped. The mist seemed to be lifting. The summit of Moel Llyfnant was
clear and the summit of Arenig Fawr kept popping out of its covering.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The climb up to Moel Lyfnant via its East flank is steep and
unremitting. There are traces of a track in places, but I find it's
best just to take a direct line to the summit rocks. I emerged at the
top almost exactly at 6:00pm. There was a stiff breeze blowing from
the East. My usual camping spot between some rocks was quite exposed
to the breeze, so I dropped down to another flat spot a few yards to
the west, which was more sheltered. I soon had the tent up and after a
quick cup of hot chocolate I went on a short wander to take some
photographs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Cader at sunrise." href="/images/2014-07-arenigs/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8499.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Cader at sunrise." title="Cader at sunrise." src="/images/2014-07-arenigs/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8499.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was hungry, so when I got back to the tent I heated some water and
had one of the Adventure Foods expedition breakfasts. This was OK, but
definitely not as good as the Bewell Foods Hot Cereal Start. I felt
quite tired so settled into my sleeping bag. About 6:30pm the mist
descended over the summit and all views were obscured.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I turned on my phone,  hoping to send some photographs home. There was excellent
reception, but it was on a different network to mine (Three).  On my
previous two visits I had been using T-Mobile, which has solid 3g
coverage o the summit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I got up sometime around midnight to find that the cloud had lifted
above the summit and I could see the lights of all the surrounding
towns. The next time I woke it was 5:30am and daylight. Looking out of
the tent I could see it was still clear, so I got out for a look
round. There was quite a bit of thick cloud higher up, particularly
around the Arans. A couple of the valleys had a covering of early
morning mist. The sun was hidden behind a bank of cloud, so there
wasn't a spectacular sunrise. I made a cup of hot chocolate and
porridge and then went back to bed. I got up again about 6:15 am to
take some more photographs and pack up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Early morning mist." href="/images/2014-07-arenigs/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8505.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Early morning mist." title="Early morning mist." src="/images/2014-07-arenigs/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8505.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I planned to go over to Foel Boeth and Moel y Slates having been here
twice without climbing them. However, as I was packing the tent away
about 7:00am the mist descended again. I could see glimpses of the sun
above it, so hoped it might clear. It wasn't to be and if anything it
got thicker. I decide that walking over Foel Boeth would be a waste of
time if I couldn't see anything. It looked a pretty uninspiring hill
even in clear visibility. I set off down the North ridge following a
compass bearing, as there is no clear path, but numerous sheep tracks
which wander off in various ransom directions giving you the illusion
that you are following a path. I was quite a way down the ridge before
I emerged from the cloud. My big toe on my left foot was hurting. I
had bruised it on my Carneddeau trip and now it felt as though the
nail was coming off. I scrambled down the last bit of the ridge to
join the farm track.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I decided to follow the track from Amnodd-bwll that lead towards the
railway track, rather the one that takes the higher ground and goes
past Amnodd-wen. This latter track has a section which is sunken next
to a dry stone wall. On both my previous visits I have got very wet
feet as there is no real way of avoiding the boggy section. The track
that leads to the railway initially goes through the forest, thus has
restricted views. Once out of the forest the views are just as good as
those from the higher track. I reached the railway track and started
to follow it. It doesn't seem to get much
traffic and some sections were covered by long grass. I met a couple of cows with
calves on the track, but shooed them up onto the hillside, so I
wouldn't have to walk to close to them. The railway track emerged onto
the road. This final section along the road back to the quarry
seems much longer than it actually is. Once back at the truck I had
another cup of hot chocolate.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Whilst I was walking back along the railway track the summits had all
cleared. I did consider doing another walk to take advantage of the
clear conditions. Unfortunately, I had to drive back through Chester
to pick up my daughter in the early afternoon, which didn't leave
enough time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Although the weather had been much better on my last two trips to the
Arenigs, it hadn't been too bad this time.  I hadn't seen the
spectacular sunsets and sunrises of my previous two trips, but the
mist filled valleys at dawn compensated. Plus I always enjoy a summit
camp away from everyone else.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>mountaineering</category><category>tripreport</category><guid>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2014-06-28-arenigs/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2014 17:57:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Carneddau</title><link>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2014-05-16-carneddau/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;!– PELICAN&lt;sub&gt;BEGIN&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/sub&gt; –&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Pen Llithrig yr Wrach and Pen yr Helgi Du misted out." href="/images/2014-05-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8276.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Pen Llithrig yr Wrach and Pen yr Helgi Du misted out." title="Pen Llithrig yr Wrach and Pen yr Helgi Du misted out." src="/images/2014-05-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8276.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had wanted to get out backpacking all year, but my free time had
always coincided with periods of poor weather. Finally I could get out
for a couple of days and the forecast was good. The plan was to drive
into Cwm Eigiau and do a two day traverse. I had done a similar route
a couple of years ago, but wanted to do a similar route in reverse
starting at Pen Llithrig y Wrach and going clockwise around the ridge.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;!– PELICAN&lt;sub&gt;END&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/sub&gt; –&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last year various bits of the road into Cwm Egiau were widened and new
passing places installed and the road was closed for several
months. Before these improvements there were only a very limited
number of places where passing was possible, so meeting a mini bus
coming in the opposite direction usually involved a fair bit of
reversing. This wasn't much fun as there are several hair pin bends
and some 20% gradients. As luck would have it, I met a large mini bus coming
down just next to the first gate. I had to bump up onto the grass pull
in next to the gate to let it past. At the second gate I passed
someone walking up the road and he kindly to closed the gate for me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Llyn Eigiau appears from the mist." href="/images/2014-05-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8280.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Llyn Eigiau appears from the mist." title="Llyn Eigiau appears from the mist." src="/images/2014-05-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8280.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
The weather forecast was for early morning mist over the summits to
clear by midday. However, at 10:30am the summits were all misted out
and I wondered if I had made the right choice in coming up into Cwm
Eigiau.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There were only a couple of cars parked in the car park. While I was
getting ready the man who had opened the gate stopped to chat with
me. He was originally from Dolgarrog, but was now living in
Manchester. He had camped further down the road and was going to walk
over to Llyn Colwyd before going back to Dolgarrog.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Moel Siabod from Pen Llithrig yr Wrach." href="/images/2014-05-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8282.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Moel Siabod from Pen Llithrig yr Wrach." title="Moel Siabod from Pen Llithrig yr Wrach." src="/images/2014-05-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8282.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I bumped into him again when I went up to the reservoir to fill my
water bottles. He asked if he could walk with me up towards Pen
Llithrig yr Wrach. We set off along a track that leads up to an old
quarry on the slopes of Pen Llithrig yr Wrach. I hadn't been this way
before and there are some impressive holes in the ground, which I
presume are old mine entrances. Part of the way along the track I
realised that I had left my stove in the car. My walking companion
very kindly offered to let me borrow his, but I said that I would
manage OK. When we got to the ridge he turned off to descend towards
Llyn Colwyd. I plodded on up the summit of Pen y Llithrig y Wrach,
which was still covered in mist. Luckily the mist cleared just as I
reached the summit and I was able to enjoy good views while I sat and
ate my sandwich and chocolate brownie.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="The way ahead to Carnedd Llewelyn from Pen Llithrig yr Wrach." href="/images/2014-05-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8284.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="The way ahead to Carnedd Llewelyn from Pen Llithrig yr Wrach." title="The way ahead to Carnedd Llewelyn from Pen Llithrig yr Wrach." src="/images/2014-05-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8284.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I still hadn't decided what to do about the missing stove. All my
camping food was dehydrated, so without hot water I wasn't going to be
able to eat until I got back to the car. I had my Travel Tap, so I
could top up my water supplies from the various pools of water.  At
first I thought I might be able to gather enough old heather roots to
make a fire. However, there was very little old heather about and most
of it was damp.  Eventually, I decided to press on and see how I felt
later in the day. The slope up to Pen yr Helgi Du seemed harder than
the last time I did it. I stopped a couple of times on the way to the
summit.   As I descended to Bwlch Eryl
Farchog I got cramp in my legs, probably because I wasn't drinking enough water.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I enjoyed the brief scramble up to the summit of Craig yr
Ysfa. However, the long ridge leading up to Carnedd Llelwlyn was very slow
going . If I had got the stove with me, I would probably camped at
the spot Ella and I used in ??? at the foot of the final ridge, even thought it was still early
afternoon. In retrospect I should have brought more water and some
carbohydrate snacks with me. Eventually I arrived at the summit, which was covered in mist
despite being clear a few minutes earlier. Luckily, the mist cleared just long
enough for me to take a photo of Moel Siabod.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Tryfan and the Glyders from Pen yr Helgi Du." href="/images/2014-05-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8290.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Tryfan and the Glyders from Pen yr Helgi Du." title="Tryfan and the Glyders from Pen yr Helgi Du." src="/images/2014-05-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8290.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
 I thought I might camp next to the small pools of water on
Gledrffordd. At least I would have water and wouldn't be too far from
the car the next morning. I glimpsed the pools through brief clearings
in the mist. However, I wasn't at all certain how to get down to them
and the detail of that area on my Harveys BMC map didn't really give
me any clues. I was pretty certain it was a straightforward slope, but
didn't really know where I needed to turn off the main ridge and it
there would be any crags that weren't marked on my map. I set off in
the direction of Foel Goch, finding the bouldery initial section hard
going. I checked the GPS a couple of times to fix my position on the
map. It was still very misty and I couldn't see the descent to
Gledrffordd. As I lost a bit of height the mist cleared and I could
see the path clearly in front of me. I descended from the crest of the
ridge towards the path and in the distance I could see the pools of
water on Gledrffordd. I didn't feel too bad going downhill, but still
got a few attacks of cramp. I didn't have a lot of water left and
wanted to conserve it in case I couldn't find a stream.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Moel Siabod from Carnedd Llewelyn." href="/images/2014-05-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8294.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Moel Siabod from Carnedd Llewelyn." title="Moel Siabod from Carnedd Llewelyn." src="/images/2014-05-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8294.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I made may way towards Gledrffordd, I began to think it might be
more sensible to descend all the way back to the car, as I was feeling
very hungry. The prospect of lying awake all night thinking I could
eat if I continued the relatively short distance back to the car
wasn't appealing. It seemed a long way to over the grassy plateau to
the pools on Gledrffordd, but eventually I reached the rocky crest at
the end. The path disappeared into the rocks and thinking that I was
at the end of the ridge , I clambered over the rocky crest and began
to descend. I should have checked the map first!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Pen yr Helgi Du and Pen Llithrig yr Wrach from Carnedd Llewelyn." href="/images/2014-05-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8299.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Pen yr Helgi Du and Pen Llithrig yr Wrach from Carnedd Llewelyn." title="Pen yr Helgi Du and Pen Llithrig yr Wrach from Carnedd Llewelyn." src="/images/2014-05-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8299.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
The valley below was obscured by mist, but this cleared after I had
descended a couple of hundred feet. I could see that I was on the
crags (Craig Eigiau) about half way along Llyn Eigiau. Trying to
descend these was not a good idea, as the ground was steep and rocky!
Painfully I regained the crest of the ridge and began traversing along
the slope below and parallel to it. Finally, the path
descended towards a Landrover track. I was very tired and hobbled
along the track eventually, rejoining the road next to the car
park. All the way down I had passed no streams and only a few muddy
pools on Gledrffordd. I would have expected more water after the recent rains.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Carneddau Ponies." href="/images/2014-05-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8304.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Carneddau Ponies." title="Carneddau Ponies." src="/images/2014-05-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8304.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Luckily there was a bottle of water inside the truck, which I drank
before retrieving the stove and staggering off towards the
reservoir. I did think of camping at Maeneira, which from other
people's reports looked an ideal spot.  However, it wasn't marked on
my Harvey map and I wasn't sure exactly where it was. I went through
the smaller of the two gaps in the dam and splashed though a boggy
area before finding somewhere drier on slightly raised ground. I
chucked down my rucksack and went over to the reservoir to fill my
water bottles. There were several Cuckoos calling as I put the tent
up.  It was well after 10:00pm before I had the tent up and my gear
stowed inside. I made a mug of hot chocolate and had a hot cereal
start to eat. Finally, before getting into my sleeping bag I drank
another cup of hot chocolate.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A short while later it got very light. Looking outside I could see
there was a full moon. The mist over the summits from earlier had
disappeared and there was a clear starry sky.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Gledrffordd appears out of the mist." href="/images/2014-05-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8301.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Gledrffordd appears out of the mist." title="Gledrffordd appears out of the mist." src="/images/2014-05-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8301.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I woke up about 5:30am, with the sun already rising. I crawled out of
the tent and put on some water to boil for a cup of hot chocolate and
to make some porridge. I was expecting to get cramp in my legs, but apart from
feeling very sore they were OK. After eating breakfast I got out the
Tyvek sheet from my rucksack and piled all the stuff from the tent on
top of it to stop it getting wet. I took my time packing away and
enjoyed looking at the scenery.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Landrover track leading down from Craig Eigiau." href="/images/2014-05-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8305.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Landrover track leading down from Craig Eigiau." title="Landrover track leading down from Craig Eigiau." src="/images/2014-05-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8305.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In order to avoid the boggy section, I walked up to the big break in
the dam wall before rejoining the Landrover track. It seemed a long
way back to the truck and the sun was already getting hot. I was
wearing my new Montane insulated trousers which I had brought along
for camp use, as my Mammut Base Jumps were wet from yesterday. Once
back at the truck I changed into my lightweight Rab Treklites and felt
much better.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Pen Llithrig yr Wrach from the dam." href="/images/2014-05-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8310.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Pen Llithrig yr Wrach from the dam." title="Pen Llithrig yr Wrach from the dam." src="/images/2014-05-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8310.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I drove into Caernarfon and joined the A55 driving towards Bangor. I
stopped at Y Caban in Deniolen. It was only 8:50am and they didn't
open until 9:00am, so I sat on the seats outside, enjoying the
sunshine. They were having a veggie week, so my sausage sandwich was
vegetarian. I am not a vegetarian, but do enjoy veggie food. However,
I was wondering what the sausage would taste like.  I needn't have
worried as it tasted as good as the meat version. Y Caban is very
friendly and serves excellent food, highly recommended. I had a couple
of cups of coffee before setting off for Capel Curig.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Packing away the tent below the dam wall." href="/images/2014-05-carned/IMG&lt;sub&gt;8311.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Packing away the tent below the dam wall." title="Packing away the tent below the dam wall." src="/images/2014-05-carned/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;8311.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Just outside Joe Browns in Capel Curig I bumped into some old friends
from Sheffield and we had a chat.  They had been up Cnicht the day
before and were thinking of a Carneddau trip today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even though I hadn't managed to camp on a summit, it had been a
worthwhile trip and I enjoyed camping next to the reservoir. The cloud
had persisted longer than forecast, but had cleared often enough to
give me good views. Next time I'll double check to make sure I haven't
left my stove in the truck!
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>mountaineering</category><category>tripreport</category><guid>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2014-05-16-carneddau/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2014 17:57:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Arenigs Overnighter</title><link>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2013-07-20-Arenigs-Overnighter/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
*
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;!– PELICAN&lt;sub&gt;BEGIN&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/sub&gt; –&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Cotton grass on Arenig Fawr." href="/images/2013-07&lt;sub&gt;arenigs&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7650.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Cotton grass on Arenig Fawr." title="Cotton grass on Arenig Fawr." src="/images/2013-07&lt;sub&gt;arenigs&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7650.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another short trip, starting late in the day to avoid the heat. I had
done the same trip last year and enjoyed it so much, I decided to do
it again! The original inspiration for this trip came from &lt;a href="http://v-g.me.uk/Trips/T0607/T0607.htm"&gt;v-g&lt;/a&gt;
excellent site.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;!– PELICAN&lt;sub&gt;END&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/sub&gt; –&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
Last time I had parked in the small pull in near to the start of the
track leading up to Llyn Arenig Fawr. However, this left me with quite
a bit of road walking on the second day. So I decided to park in the
large area opposite the quarry at 830393, which meant I would get most
of the road walking done at the start of the first day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I left the car around 4:00pm and made my way to the start of the
track. It is possible to follow the old railway track alongside the
road, but you need to cut back to the road at one point and it seemed
simpler to just walk along the road. The temperature was gradually
cooling, but it was still very hot at around 25C. As I made my way up
the track towards Llyn Arenig Fawr I met a couple of people
descending. There was a group with a couple of tents just setting up,
below the dam wall. I had a quick look in the bothy, as I had read
that it had been vandalized recently. However, it seemed to have been
repaired as it looked in good condition.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The cotton grass was out, making the large areas of grass look much
more attractive. I also noticed what I know as "Cuckoo spit" - frothy
white liquid attached to the blades of grass.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Tarns on South ridge of Arenig Fawr." href="/images/2013-07&lt;sub&gt;arenigs&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7672.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Tarns on South ridge of Arenig Fawr." title="Tarns on South ridge of Arenig Fawr." src="/images/2013-07&lt;sub&gt;arenigs&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7672.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I filled my water bottle from the reservoir and began the plod up the
slope leading to Arenig Fawr. Last time I had followed the path that
contours all the way along the East face before finally gaining the
ridge just below the summit of Arenig Fawr. This time I wanted to gain
the ridge earlier by climbing directly up the grass slope on the
right. This would give me god views both to the East and West as I
climbed towards the summit. On my first attempt I left the path too
early and ended up regaining it a bit higher up. However, I could now
see the ridge line and on my second attempt got up onto the ridge. The
heat had made the distant views hazy, but there was still a fine
prospect of almost every peak in Snowdonia.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Summit camp on Moel Llyfnant." href="/images/2013-07&lt;sub&gt;arenigs&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7674.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Summit camp on Moel Llyfnant." title="Summit camp on Moel Llyfnant." src="/images/2013-07&lt;sub&gt;arenigs&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7674.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Reaching the summit of Arenig Fawr, I sat down next to the memorial to
the crew of the B17 Flying Fortress, which had crashed on the
slopes. There were several small wooden crosses and poppies beneath
the memorial, presumably placed there on Remembrance Day. I am not
really a fan of memorials on mountains, but there are certain historic
ones that have been there for many years. It was good that somebody
had gone to the trouble of placing the poppies beneath the plaque. I
wondered if any of the airmen's families had ever visited this spot.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Sunset over Snowdon." href="/images/2013-07&lt;sub&gt;arenigs&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7704.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Sunset over Snowdon." title="Sunset over Snowdon." src="/images/2013-07&lt;sub&gt;arenigs&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7704.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was now 6:00pm and I wanted to get to Moel Llyfnant before
sunset. I set off down the South ridge towards the area of small lakes
and grassy knolls. I needed to stock up on water. However, I expected
the small stream on the western slope leading down to the col would be
dry. I scooped some water out of one of the lakes into a Platypus and
it had a distinct green tinge. There were no obvious sources of
running water and I knew there were none on Moel Llyfnant. Luckily I
had brought my &lt;a href="http://www.drinksafe-systems.co.uk/products.php"&gt;Travel Tap&lt;/a&gt;. I don't normally bother
purifying water in the UK, as there are usually ample supplies of
clean water. However, I had anticipated a problem because of the
recent dry weather and so had brought
my Travel Tap along with me. I filled up all three one litre Platypus
bottles from the lake before walking over to the corner of the fence that marks the
start of the descent to the col below Moel Llyfnant.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I expected all the little streams were dry, as was the normally boggy
section at the col. The ascent to Moel Llyfnant is steep and
unremitting, but not too far. I sweated my way up the steep grass
taking a direct line towards the summit, popping out on the ridge only
a few yards away from the cairn.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I camped on a small sheltered area close to the summit. There was just
enough of a breeze to keep the insects away. After taking on board
lots of fluid and a Hot Cereal Start, I sat by the summit cairn and
watched the sun setting over Snowdon.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was a very warm night and I slept with the doors open. Sometime
after it went dark, I emerged from the tent to look at the stars. Even
in the middle of the night I was quite comfortable in just shirt
sleeves. I woke again shortly after 4:00pm. It was already getting
light and climbing out of the tent I could see the sky glowing red
behind Arenig Fawr. I got out the camera and took photos as the sun
climbed over the shoulder of Arenig Fawr.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Just before the sunrise over Arenig Fawr." href="/images/2013-07&lt;sub&gt;arenigs&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7715.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Just before the sunrise over Arenig Fawr." title="Just before the sunrise over Arenig Fawr." src="/images/2013-07&lt;sub&gt;arenigs&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7715.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had packed up by 7:00am and began descending the North Ridge towards
the abanodoned cottage of Amnod-bwll. Last time I had retraced my
ascent route back to the col and had bushwacked through long tussocky
wet bog to the edge of the plantation, which was really
unpleasant. The North ridge was much nicer, with short grass and no
boggy bits. There are traces of a path, intermingled with lots of
misleading sheep tracks. However, if you just head on a bearing
towards Amnodd-bwll you will emerge onto a farm track near to the
bottom of the hill.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Moel Llyfnant from the forestry track." href="/images/2013-07&lt;sub&gt;arenigs&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7741.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Moel Llyfnant from the forestry track." title="Moel Llyfnant from the forestry track." src="/images/2013-07&lt;sub&gt;arenigs&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7741.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
From Amnodd-bwll I followed the forestry road. There comes a point near
to the ruined buildings of Amnodd-wen where the track divides. I couldn't
remember which branch I should take and set off down the left hand
one. After a few hundred yards I could see that this was the wrong way
and would bring me out much too far up the road, so I back
tracked. The right hand branch of the path soon leads to a very boggy
section next to a wall. Whichever way you choose is wet, even in the
current drought conditions. After a short distance I reached a style
beyond which the splash fest became a farm track. I descended past the
farm and onto a recently made track above the railway line. This
emerged onto the road only about a kilometre from the car.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>mountaineering</category><category>tripreport</category><guid>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2013-07-20-Arenigs-Overnighter/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2013 17:56:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Moelwyns Cloud Inversion</title><link>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2013-07-06-moelwyns-cloud-inversion/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;!– PELICAN&lt;sub&gt;BEGIN&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/sub&gt; –&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb" title="Tremadoc Bay from Moelwyn Bach." href="/images/2013-07-moelwyns/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7584.jpg&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Tremadoc Bay from Moelwyn Bach." title="Tremadoc Bay from Moelwyn Bach." src="/images/2013-07-moelwyns/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7584.jpg&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
My son was doing his D of E Bronze expedition over the weekend,
starting from Llandegla. The weather forecast was for hot and sunny
conditions over the next few days. I didn't want to waste the
opportunity for an overnight trip, but has to be back home at midday
on the Saturday morning. However, we wouldn't be
arriving at Llandegla until about 7:00pm, which left very limited
time for me to drive into Snowdonia and get up to a summit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;!– PELICAN&lt;sub&gt;END&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/sub&gt; –&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Sunset at this time of year was 9:37pm. The closest mountains,
the Arans, only about 30mins drive away. I had completed an
Arans circuit a couple of weeks ago and didn't want to go back so
soon. Finally, I decided on the Mooelwyns, which were about an hour
and fifteen minutes drive from Llandegla. I would be completing about
half the walk after sunset, but navigation was simple, just follow
the ridge and at this time of year it never goes properly dark.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb" title="Nantlle Ridge and Moelwyn Mawr." href="/images/2013-07-moelwyns/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7587.jpg&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Nantlle Ridge and Moelwyn Mawr." title="Nantlle Ridge and Moelwyn Mawr." src="/images/2013-07-moelwyns/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7587.jpg&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I arrived at the car park in Tanygrisiau shortly before 8:30pm. I had
packed my rucksack before leaving home, so all I needed to do was get
out of the car and start walking. My plan was to walk up the reservoir
road to Llyn Stwlan, climb Moelwyn Bach, descend back to the col and
then climb Moelwyn Mawr where I would camp on the summit. I had done
this trip in &lt;a href="http://www.ian-barton.com/posts/2012/Apr/13/a-trip-over-the-moelwyns/"&gt;April&lt;/a&gt; last year, when I experienced a hail storm on my
ascent of Moelwyn Bach and the summit was misted out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Wandering up the reservoir road munching a cheese and onion sandwich,
I met two groups of two people descending. I soon reached the dam
wall and crossed the stream below it. I couldn't remember if it was
easy to access Llyn Stwlan from this side, so I collected water from
the outfall pipe below the dam. Once I had climbed the concrete steps
at the far side of the dam, I would see that I could easily have
collected my water from the lake, something to remember for next time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb" title="Tremadoc Bay from Moelwyn Bach." href="/images/2013-07-moelwyns/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7620.jpg&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Tremadoc Bay from Moelwyn Bach." title="Tremadoc Bay from Moelwyn Bach." src="/images/2013-07-moelwyns/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7620.jpg&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The route from Llyn Stwlan follows a fairly direct line over semi
boggy ground to the col between Moelwyn Mawr and Moelwyn Bach. I
reached the col at around 9:25pm in time to see the sun setting. I
dumped my sack and managed to get to the summit of Moelwyn Bach before
the sun disappeared completely. I sat on the summit cairn and watched
it disappear over the summit of the Nantlle Ridge and Molewyn
Mawr.After taking some photos I retraced my steps to the col. I had
left my sack in plain view near to the path. There wasn't anyone else
about at this time and I didn't want to lose sight of it in the
gathering gloom.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb" title="Sunrise over Moel-yr-hydd." href="/images/2013-07-moelwyns/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7623.jpg&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Sunrise over Moel-yr-hydd." title="Sunrise over Moel-yr-hydd." src="/images/2013-07-moelwyns/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7623.jpg&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The ascent of Craigysgafn involves a pleasant scramble. Much better
than my &lt;a href="http://www.ian-barton.com/posts/2012/Apr/13/a-trip-over-the-moelwyns/"&gt;last&lt;/a&gt; visit when this section was more like a winter climb,
with the rocks covered in verglas and hail. The ascent to Moelwyn
Mawr was much longer than I remembered and it was 11:00pm when I
arrived at the summit cairn. Even though the sun had disappeared
nearly two hours before, it was still light enough to see without a
head torch.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb" title="Mist drifting around Moel-yr-hydd." href="/images/2013-07-moelwyns/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7625.jpg&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Mist drifting around Moel-yr-hydd." title="Mist drifting around Moel-yr-hydd." src="/images/2013-07-moelwyns/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7625.jpg&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I set up the tent on a patch of grass close to the summit cairn. As I
had been climbing towards the summit I had noticed the valleys below
me starting to fill with cloud. I made a hot drink and some porridge
and it was nearly midnight when I go into my sleeping bag. At around
4:00am an attack of cramp had me hopping about outside the tent. The
sun was due to rise shortly after 4:30am, but already there was a red
tinge in the Eastern sky. All the surrounding valleys were full of
mist, with the odd sliver blowing over the summit. Only the tops of
the mountains were visible.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I crawled back into the tent and watched the sun rising through the
door. As the sun started to come up, the fragments of mist on the
summit dispersed and I was treated to the best inversion I have seen
in Wales. I sat outside the tent for a couple of hours watching as
the heat of the rising sun made caused the mist in below to swirl and
change shape.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb" title="Early morning light on Moelwyn Bach." href="/images/2013-07-moelwyns/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7627.jpg&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Early morning light on Moelwyn Bach." title="Early morning light on Moelwyn Bach." src="/images/2013-07-moelwyns/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7627.jpg&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I packed up around 7:00am and began to make my way downwards and over
to Moel-yr-hydd. By the time I had reached the summit the heat of the
sun had caused the mist to rise although, Moel-yr-hydd was still
clear. I descended into the mist towards the old quarry
workings. Eventually some old buildings appeared out of the mist and
I followed a path. However, this ended on top of a steep slope of
slate scree. Not wishing to scramble down, I back-tracked to the
buildings and found the track that leads down through the various
levels. I soon dropped below the mist and enjoyed a pleasant walk
through Cwmorthin back to the road. I drove the short distance to the
lakeside cafe for a second breakfast.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>mountaineering</category><category>tripreport</category><guid>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2013-07-06-moelwyns-cloud-inversion/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2013 17:56:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Arans</title><link>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2013-06-10-Arans/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Craig Cywarch." href="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7219.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Craig Cywarch." title="Craig Cywarch." src="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7219.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally a period of sunny weather. I had wanted to get out for an
overnight trip, but the weather had put paid to any trips so far this
year. After dropping the children off at the school bus I set off for
North Wales. I still hadn't decided exactly where I was going, but on
my way over the A5104 made up my mind to have a go at the Arans
traverse and camp on Glasgwm. This was a trip that I had been thinking
about for some time, as I had never climbed Glasgwm. After several
trips over the Arans in indifferent weather, I had wanted to save the
circuit for a settled period of fine weather.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;!– PELICAN&lt;sub&gt;END&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/sub&gt; –&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The plan was to park in Cwm Cowarch, then walk up Hengwm and over the
summit of Aran Fawddwy followed by a crossing of the boggy along the
boardwalks and then a final pull up Glasgwm, where I would camp next
to Llyn y Fign. The next morning I would follow my route of ascent
back to the path leading down into Cwm Cwyarch and so back to the car park.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Aran Fawddwy and Craiglyn Dyfi." href="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7229.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Aran Fawddwy and Craiglyn Dyfi." title="Aran Fawddwy and Craiglyn Dyfi." src="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7229.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I packed my rucksack and emptied a bottle of flavoured water into one
of my Platypus bottles. I set off from the car park shortly after
11:00am heading for Hengwm. Just after I had crossed the stream a few
hundred yards from the car park, I realized that I had left the
Platypus with the flavoured water in the car. Rather than go back for
it, I filled another Platypus up from the river. This wasn't really
enough water for the whole day, but I thought I would be
able to get more water higher up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Memorial with Cadair Idris in the background." href="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7234.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Memorial with Cadair Idris in the background." title="Memorial with Cadair Idris in the background." src="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7234.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Walking up Hengwm I was in the shade, which made for pleasant walking
as it was very hot in the sun. On the far side of the valley I had a
perfect view of Craig Cwyarch, with its great rock climbs like "Will
o' the Wisp" and Acheron. Cresting the slope up to the col, I decided
against plodding through the peat hags to visit the top of Waun Goch
and struck out up the slope towards Drysgol. When I reached the
memorial at Drws Bach I stopped for a drink and ate the slice of
Victoria sponge I had brought with me. The summit ridge of Aran
Fawddwy was completely clear and there were great views over the
steep East face and down to Craiglyn Dyfi, where I had pitched the
Voyager Superlite last year for the first time in pouring rain.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Rhinogs in the distance." href="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7235.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Rhinogs in the distance." title="Rhinogs in the distance." src="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7235.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After a short rest, I continued up towards the summit of Aran
Fawddwy. On the way I crossed a ladder style and noticed a small
plaque with the OS grid reference on it. On the rest of the walk I saw
that every style now had one of these plaques. I can't help thinking
that putting these everywhere is destroying the remoteness that many
people seek in the mountains.  There was someone resting near to the
cairn who said that he was reccing a walk he was planning to lead at
the wearing the weekend. After he left I got out my lunch and ate it
with my feet dangling over the drop above Craiglyn Dyfi. I thought
that there would be pools of water around the summit, but I could find
any. I new that there were several big pools near to the summit of
Aran Benllyn. However, I was too lazy to walk the extra distance to
Aran Benllyn and thought I would be certain to find more water before
my ascent of Glasgwm. This turned out to be a bad decision!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="OS grid reference on a ladder style." href="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7245.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="OS grid reference on a ladder style." title="OS grid reference on a ladder style." src="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7245.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
When I had finished lunch I started to make my way back down the
summit pyramid to join the fence that would take me to the bottom of
Glasgwm. I could see the cairn on the summit clearly, but knew that
it was a fair distance to walk before I reached the final slopes up
to its summit. Just after I crossed the ladder style at the start of
the fence, I met another man who was sitting admiring the view. In the
whole day I only saw three people.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Aran Benllyn from Aran Fawddwy." href="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7256.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Aran Benllyn from Aran Fawddwy." title="Aran Benllyn from Aran Fawddwy." src="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7256.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Luckily the ground was fairly dry, with only a couple of the boarded
sections over the bogs covering significantly wet sections. It seemed
a long way to where the path met the one coming up from Cwm Cywarch
and I didn't find any sources of water to replenish my supply. By the
time I reached the slope that leads up to Glasgwm, I was feeling a bit
dehydrated. Foolishly, I didn't walk the extra couple of hundred yards
to find the start of the stream that flows down to Cwm Cywarch, but
started off in the opposite direction to find the path that climbs up
Glasgwm.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The ascent of Glasgwm was a steep pull. The path follows the fence
almost all the way, with a steep scree section just below the
summit. Finally I saw Llyn Bach and the summit cairn. Sitting on the
cairn I could see Llyn Figyn just below the summit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first job was to go straight down to the lake and drink lots of
water. Once I had rehydrated, I looked around for a camp site. There
was a perfect flat grassy patch that was near to the ladder style. I
soon had the tent pitched and lay down inside to escape from the sun
for a few minutes and rest.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Tent near Llyn Figyn." href="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7269.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Tent near Llyn Figyn." title="Tent near Llyn Figyn." src="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7269.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There was plenty of daylight left, so once I had eaten tea I set off
around the summit to explore. Although it had been a warm day, there
was very little haze. There was just enough breeze to keep the
insects away. I was quite tired, but wanted to get some pictures of
the sunset, which was around 9:30pm. Shortly after nine I got out of
the tent and wandered around taking photos. Finally I sat next to the
summit cairn and watched the sun drop below the horizon.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Sunset." href="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7311.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Sunset." title="Sunset." src="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7311.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Crawling back into the tent, I fell asleep almost immediately. When I
woke up it was light. Glancing at my watch it was shortly after
5:00am. I had wanted to get some pictures of the sunrise, which was
just before 5:00am. Scrambling out of the tent I was just in time to
get some photos of the sun rising over Aran Fawddwy.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I made some breakfast with &lt;a href="http://www.mountaintrails.org.uk/"&gt;Mountain Trails&lt;/a&gt; excellent porridge and
began to pack up the tent. I didn't want to be late back and it was
obviously going to be another hot day, so I was packed up and ready to
descend shortly after 6:00am. Taking my time, so I could enjoy the
views I retraced my line of ascent along the fence. I enjoyed the
steep descent into Cwm Cywarch. The sun was beginning to illuminate
the valley and the shadows formed as it rose were making all sorts of
interesting shapes over the valley. Lost in my own thoughts I walked
straight past the car park, not realizing my mistake for about a
quarter of a mile.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Sunrise over Aran Fawddwy." href="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7315.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Sunrise over Aran Fawddwy." title="Sunrise over Aran Fawddwy." src="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7315.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It had been a memorable trip. Perfect weather, a perfect wild camping
spot and almost deserted mountains.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I made some porridge for breakfast and began to pack up the
tent. I didn't want to be late back and it was obviously going to be
another hot day, so I was packed up and ready to descend shortly after
6:00am. Taking my time, so I could enjoy the views I retraced my line
of ascent along the fence.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Boards on N
Ridge of Aran Benllyn." href="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;7219.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Boards on N
Ridge of Aran Benllyn." title="Boards on N
Ridge of Aran Benllyn." src="/images/2013-06-03&lt;sub&gt;arans&lt;/sub&gt;/thumb.IMG&lt;sub&gt;7219.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>mountaineering</category><category>tripreport</category><guid>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2013-06-10-Arans/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2013 17:56:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Cross Fell</title><link>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2013-04-05_cross_fell/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I was staying with the family near to Appleby for a few days. The
cold clear weather of the last few weeks looked set to continue for a
few more days at least. I wanted to get out and walk up something,
but only had half a day to spare. I could see Cross Fell over the
other side of the valley and I can't remember when I was last up
there, so a return visit seemed in order.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I hadn't got a map, but my brother-in-law kindly lent me one. Also,
as I hadn't planned on doing any high level walking, I didn't have
any winter kit with me. From what I could see from down in the valley
most of the snow had been scoured off the slopes by the wind, so I
hope I could make my way round any patches of hard snow or ice. I
drove over to Culgaith and looked at my map to see how I would get to
Kirkland where the walk started. This was when I discovered that my
brother-in-law had given me the wrong map! A quick trip to Penrith
and a wait until 9:00am, when WH Smith opened, solved this
problem. However, it meant that getting back by 2:00pm was going to
be hard.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I parked up next to the church in Kirkland and consulted my new map
about the fastest route to the summit. I had enough clothing to keep
warm, but only my Inov8 Roclite's
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>mountaineering</category><category>tripreport</category><guid>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2013-04-05_cross_fell/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2013 17:55:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Moel Siabod In Winter</title><link>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2013-03-28-moel-siabod-in-winter/</link><dc:creator>Ian Barton.</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I had wanted to do an overnight trip to North Wales for some time. I
am not keen on camping in the Winter months, as there is so little
daylight and I don't really want to spend 12-14hrs in the
tent. However, it's now light until about 7:00pm and sunrise is around
6:00am. This spring has seen an unusually cold spell of weather with
the tops returning to true winter conditions, as temperature remained
below freezing for many days.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Moel Siabod from the Farm Track." href="/images/2013-03&lt;sub&gt;moel&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;siabod&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;6781.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Moel Siabod from the Farm Track." title="Moel Siabod from the Farm Track." src="/images/2013-03&lt;sub&gt;moel&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;siabod&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;6781.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I decided on a trip up Moel Siabod because I wanted to use our new
DSLR to take some night time photos and do a series of time lapse
sunset and sunrise pictures. The weather forecast seemed good with
predictions of clouds above the summits, but temperatures around -6C
at 800m.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I dropped my son off in Chester and continued round the A55 to
Llanberis. Since my mountaineering boots have worn out and I only
have crampons suitable for B3 boots, I needed to get something
suitable for my Meindl walking boots. Rather than buy another pair of
crampons I decided to get some &lt;a href="http://www.kahtoola.com/microspikes.php"&gt;Kahtoola Microspikes&lt;/a&gt; . These were duly
purchased from V12 and after a quick sausage sandwich in Pete's Eats
I set off for Capel Curig.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Final section up to the summit." href="/images/2013-03&lt;sub&gt;moel&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;siabod&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;6785.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Final section up to the summit." title="Final section up to the summit." src="/images/2013-03&lt;sub&gt;moel&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;siabod&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;6785.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
There was a sign and barriers at the bottom of the Pass saying the
road was closed. However, it looked fine to me and there as traffic
coming down. The road was clear but either side of the top of the pass
there were diggers clearing old drifts. I just followed the gritter and had
no problem getting through.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Parking near the North London Club hut I began to sort out my
rucksack. I had quite a bit of extra gear, including an ice axe the
DSLR, a tripod and an extra lens. Luckily, everything just fitted into
my POD black ice. It was above freezing in the car park, but once I
walked up the track to the farm it was back below
freezing. I had hoped to collect water from one of the lakes or a
stream, but everything was frozen solid.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Looking towards the Moelwyns." href="/images/2013-03&lt;sub&gt;moel&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;siabod&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;6788.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Looking towards the Moelwyns." title="Looking towards the Moelwyns." src="/images/2013-03&lt;sub&gt;moel&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;siabod&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;6788.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Rather than climb the Ddear Ddu ridge, I had decided to climb the
steep slope at the end of the farm track, which is my normal descent
route. This has a couple of steep sections up onto the main ridge. I
stopped half way up the first of the steep sections to put on the
Microspikes. These turned out to be an excellent buy and coped with
varied conditions I encountered including iron hard neve and water
ice. After what seemed to be a long pull, I reached the ladder styles
at the start of the summit ridge. There was a very cold wind blowing
from the East, but the effort of dragging a heavy sack uphill had kept
me warm. The easterly wind had deposited loads of snow in the lee of
the ridge. There was a hard crust on top, but I broke through every
few steps, which made for very slow going. I crabbed my way round the
summit ridge until the summit trig point came into view. Just below
the summit, I spoke to a few people who were descending and when I got
to the trig point there was someone in a bothy bag next to it. I moved
over to the stone shelter, which was slightly less exposed to the wind
and ate some cake.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatr"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Looking back along the summit ridge." href="/images/2013-03&lt;sub&gt;moel&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;siabod&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;6795.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Looking back along the summit ridge." title="Looking back along the summit ridge." src="/images/2013-03&lt;sub&gt;moel&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;siabod&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;6795.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had a quick look at my flat camping spot overlooking just t the
north west of the summmit. The snow wasn't too deep there, but there was quite a bit of
spindrift blowing about. Since I didn't have any water, I would have
to melt snow and the nearest convenient big drifts would be some way from
the tent. I hadn't felt too well on the ascent.
Although the cloud was well above the summits there was no sunshine,
which made for very flat contrast and there wouldn't any opportunity
to photograph the stars. As it was only
about 3:30pm I would have plenty of time to descend if I wanted to.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="HTML"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;div class="photofloatl"&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;a class="fancybox-thumb" rel="fancybox-thumb"  title="Sheltering in a bothy bag on the summit." href="/images/2013-03&lt;sub&gt;moel&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;siabod&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;6797.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img
 width="200" alt="Sheltering in a bothy bag on the summit." title="Sheltering in a bothy bag on the summit." src="/images/2013-03&lt;sub&gt;moel&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;siabod&lt;/sub&gt;/IMG&lt;sub&gt;6797.JPG&lt;/sub&gt;" /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
After considering the options for a while, I made the decision to
descend and began to retrace my tracks. Almost immediately I
experienced a pain in my right hip, which was both sharp and
nagging. Although I had fallen over a couple of times and my legs were
suffering from the effects of keeping breaking through the crust, I
couldn't recall anything specific that would cause the pain. As I
ploughed on downwards I had to take frequent rests. The microspikes
worked brilliantly on the steep descent and at no time did I feel
insecure. I had another long rest when I reached the farm track and at
increasingly frequent intervals on the way down. Finally I reached the
car, where I made myself a hot drink.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
The hip didn't hurt if I was stationary, but only when I walked. After
a two hour drive home, I could barely hobble into the house. Luckily
after a nights rest it seems to have improved, so I think it's
probably just muscular.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Gear analysis.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>mountaineering</category><category>tripreport</category><guid>https://ianbarton.com/posts/2013-03-28-moel-siabod-in-winter/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2013 17:55:48 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>